翻译: FENGYUDEER
电波字幕组 诚心诚译
校对: Kyle
后期: 秋小豚
注意了 风暴依旧在向西移动
...and I'll tell you what, the storm system's still moving west.
你在看什么呢 Caroline
What are you looking at, Caroline?
看风 妈妈
The wind, Mom.
他们说飓风要来了
They say the hurricane is coming.
我感觉我在船上
I'm on a boat.
随波漂流着
I'm drifting.
要我为你做点什么吗 妈妈
Can I do anything for you, Mom?
让你舒服点
Make anything easier?
哦 宝贝
Oh, sugar...
没有什么可做的了
There's nothing left to do.
事已至此 就这样了
Is what it is.
想睁眼都变得更难了
Finding it harder to keep my eyes open.
我感觉嘴里都是棉絮
My mouth's full of cotton.
好了 好了 Daisy女士
There, there, Miss Daisy.
你会把自己抓烂的
You gonna scratch yourself to ribbons.
妈妈 你还想加大药量吗
Do you want any more medication, Mother?
医生说你想要多少就用多少
Doctor said you could have as much as you want.
这样大家都不用遭罪
No need for anybody to suffer.
一个朋友告诉我 她都没有机会
A friend told me that she never had the chance
跟她妈妈告别
to say goodbye to her mother.
- 我想  - 没事的
- I wanted to... - it's okay.
我想告诉你 我会很想你的
I wanted to tell you how much I'm gonna miss you so...
妈
Mom.
好了 Caroline
Oh, Caroline.
你害怕吗
Are you afraid?
我很好奇
I'm curious.
接下来会怎么样呢
What comes next?
他们在1918年建造了火车站
They built the train station in 1918.
车站开始运营的那天 我爸爸也去了
My father was there the day it opened.
他说 那天请了
He said they had
铜管乐队去表演
a tuba band playing.
还请了全南方最优秀的钟表匠
They had the finest clockmaker in all of the South
打造了那座绝美的钟
to build that glorious clock.
钟表匠叫
His name was...
Gateau先生
Mr. Gateau.
Gateau在法语中意为蛋糕
蛋糕先生
Mr. Cake.
他娶了伊文格琳县的一位克里奥尔人
He was married to a Creole of Evangeline Parish
Creole 带有法国血统的人
并且有了个儿子
and they had a son.
Gateau先生天生盲障
Mr. Gateau was, from birth, absolutely blind.
他们的儿子到了年龄 就去参军了
When their son was old enough, he joined the army.
他们祈祷上帝能保佑儿子免受灾难
And they prayed God would keep him out of harm's way.
多月以来 他什么都没做 只专注打造那个钟
For months, he did nothing but work on that clock.
一天
One day,
他们收到了一封信
a letter came.
Gateau先生结束当晚的工作后
And Mr. Gateau, done for the night,
独自上楼睡觉了
went up, alone, to bed.
他们的儿子被送了回来
And their son came home.
他们把他埋在家族墓地里
They buried him in the family plot,
等他们去世 将和儿子一起埋在这里
where he would be with them when their time came.
蛋糕先生继续打造那座钟
Mr. Cake worked on his clock,
全力以赴 终于完成
laboring to finish.
那是一个值得纪念的早晨
It was a morning to remember.
爸爸说那里人山人海
Papa said there were people everywhere.
连Teddy Roosevelt都去了
Even Teddy Roosevelt came.
美国第26任总统
钟是倒着走的
It's running backwards!
我就是这么设计的
I made it that way
这样 也许那些我们在战争中失去的孩子们
so that perhaps the boys that we lost in the war
会死而复生 回到家乡
might stand and come home again.
回家耕种
Home to farm,
工作
work,
生儿育女
have children.
过着充实 长久的生活
To live long, full lives.
也许我的儿子会回来
Perhaps my own son might come home again.
如有冒犯 还请原谅
I'm sorry if I've offended anybody.
希望你们喜欢我的钟
I hope you enjoy my clock.
蛋糕先生从此杳无音信
Mr. Cake was never seen again.
有人说他因心碎而死
Some say he died of a broken heart.
有人说他下海远航了
Some say he went to sea.
打扰一下
Excuse me.
你介意我打个电话吗 我让别人在照看我儿子
Do you mind if I make a call? Somebody's watching my little boy.
去吧
Sure.
希望我没有让你失望
I hope I haven't disappointed you.
你怎么会让我失望呢
You couldn't disappoint me.
我知道 我自己没什么本事
Well, I know I don't have much to show for myself.
去把我深色的手提箱找出来
Find my dark suitcase.
里面有一本日记
There's a diary.
这本吗
This?
你能读给我听吗
Could you read it to me?
这就是你想做的事吗
Is this what you want to do?
我想读它有百余遍了
I tried to read it a hundred different times.
妈 这也不是
Mom, it's not exactly...
宝贝 我只是想听你的声音
It's just the sound of your voice, darling.
好
Okay.
时间是1985年4月4日
It's dated April 4th, 1985.
地点写的是新奥尔良
And it says New Orleans.
"这是我的遗嘱
"This is my last will and testament.
我没有留下什么 没有财产 没有钱 什么都没有
I don't have much to leave, few possessions, no money, really.
我将像来到这个世界的时候一样
I will go out of this world
孑然一身地离开这个世界
the same way I came in, alone and with nothing.
我所拥有的 就是我的故事
All I have is my story,
趁我还记得 我要把它写下来
And I'm writing it now while I still remember it.
我叫Benjamin Benjamin Button"
My name is Benjamin. Benjamin Button."
我出身在一个不同寻常的时间里
And I was born under unusual circumstances.
那是一战结束的那天
The First World War had ended,
别人告诉我 那是一个适合出生的好夜晚
and I've been told it was an especially good night to be born.
战争终于结束了
Thank God it's over!
我们赢了
We won the war!
大战结束了
The Great War is over!
你在这儿干嘛
What are you doing here?
Thomas
Thomas,
恐怕她快不行了
I'm afraid she's going to die.
什么
What?
够了 你们所有人都离她远点儿
That's enough. All of you, get away from her.
我尽可能快地赶来了 街上都是人
I came as quickly as I could. The streets are filled with people.
Thomas
Thomas.
向我保证 他会有容身之所
Promise me he has a place.
会的
Yeah.
她为我失去了生命
She gave her life for me.
正因如此 我一直心怀感激
And for that, I am forever grateful.
Button先生
Mr. Button.
Thomas
Thomas!
Thomas.
Thomas 你要去哪里
Thomas? Where are you going?
嘿 你在那儿干什么
Hey! What are you doing there?
你怀里抱的是什么
What do you have there?
- 来 Queenie  - 别这样 Weathers先生
- Come on, Queenie. - Now, Mr. Weathers!
不要嘛 你也知道
Come on, now, you know
我在这里还有一堆活要干呢
I ain't got nothing but work to do around here.
- 没事 就耽误一点时间  - 别这么傻了
- Come on. Just take some time. - Stop all this foolishness.
空气真好
The air is sweet.
你今晚格外迷人 Queenie小姐
You look very handsome tonight, Miss Queenie.
是我见过的最美的人
Handsome as I've ever seen.
棕色很衬你的眼睛
The brown matches your eyes.
哎呀 别说了
Oh, hush!
看看你 你也不邋遢啊
Let's see here. You ain't no slouch yourself.
Hambert回来了
Hambert's back in town.
他的腿没了 但好歹回来了
He came home legless, but he's home.
我知道你曾经喜欢他
I know you were sweet on him one time.
喜欢得过火了
Sweeter than I should've been.
Simone女士把自己尿湿了
Miss Simone messed herself.
哦 我的神啊
Oh, sweet Jesus.
她再这样就要给她穿尿布了
She got to stop doing that or it's diapers for her.
- 我马上去 Jameson女士  - 别走嘛 Queenie 过来
- I'll be right there, Miss Jameson! - Now, Queenie, now come on.
Queenie马上就去
Okay, Queenie'll be right there.
外面多好啊
It's awful nice out here.
在外面待一会儿吧 你好好轻松一下
Come on out back for a moment. Take your mind off things.
你这个坏人
You're so bad.
- 天 怎么回事  - 这是什么啊
- What in God's name? - What's this?
哦 上帝做了什么啊
Oh, the Lord done something here.
希望我刚没有踩伤他
Hope I didn't hurt it none stepping on it like that.
我们最好让警察来处理
We best leave that for the police.
可怜的小生命
Poor baby.
我去找警察
I'll go.
肯定没有人愿意收留他 来 宝贝
It's for sure nobody wanted to keep it. Come on, baby.
Queenie 你在哪儿 Queenie
Queenie? Where are you, Queenie?
你先憋着 你去看一下
Hold your water! You go deal with it.
没事的 快去 我马上来
Okay. No, go, I'll be back.
Queenie 亲爱的 她又把自己尿湿了
Queenie, Apple, she went and messed herself all over again!
Jane Childress 给她洗个澡
Jane Childress, start her a bath!
管好你自己的事 Duprey太太
And mind your own business, Mrs. Duprey.
你也快要尿裤子了
You'll be messing yourself soon enough.
有人偷了我的项链
Somebody stole my necklace.
好 Hollister太太 我马上来 好吗
Okay. All right, Mrs. Hollister, I'll be right with you, okay?
回楼上去 听见了吗
Go on back upstairs, hear?
你丑得就像一个破罐子
You are as ugly as an old pot
但你仍是上帝的孩子
but you're still a child of God.
Queenie 亲爱的 你不来她不肯洗澡
Queenie, Apple, she won't take a bath without you!
饶了我吧
Mercy.
我就来了
I'll be right there!
好了 你就在这里等我 好吗
Okay. You just wait right here for me now, okay?
这珍珠项链是我姐姐送的 我哪儿都找不到
My sister gave me those pearls. I can't find them anywhere.
有人一直在偷我的珠宝
Somebody's been stealing my jewelry.
它们就在这儿呢 Hollister太太 你看
They're right here, Mrs. Hollister. See?
就在你那白皙的脖子上呢
Right around your pretty white neck.
好了 不要再说话了
Now, come on. Hush all that noise.
- Rose医生还在吗  - 我不知道
- Is Dr. Rose still here? - I don't know.
你的心脏很健康
Your heart is strong.
但要避免任何过度刺激
You just want to avoid any undue stimulation.
我相信诸位女士会帮我的 对吗
I trust you ladies will help me out with that?
我有事相求 你能下楼来一下吗
I have something. Could you come downstairs?
我从没见过这种东西 白内障导致他几乎失明
Never seen anything like it. Nearly blind from cataracts.
不知道他能否听见 他的骨骼表明他患有严重关节炎
I'm not sure if he can hear. His bones indicate severe arthritis.
他的皮肤失去了弹性
His skin has lost all elasticity,
四肢也已经硬化
and his hands and feet are ossified.
他表现出来的衰竭
He shows all the deterioration,
和虚弱 一点都不像新生儿
the infirmities, not of a newborn,
而像是一个行将就木的耄耋老人
but of a man well in his 80s on his way to the grave.
他要死了吗
He's dying?
在他的生活开始前 他的身体就要辜负他了
His body is failing him before his life's begun.
他是哪来的
Where'd he come from?
我姐姐的孩子 从拉斐特来的
My sister's child. From Lafayette.
她遭遇了不幸
She had an unfortunate adventure.
这个可怜的孩子更惨 生来是白人
The poor child, he got the worst of it. Come out white.
有地方专门收留这些弃婴的 Queenie
There are places for unwanted babies like these, Queenie.
这里可养不起他了
No room for another mouth to feed here.
尽管Nolan基金会是出于好意
The Nolan Foundation, despite their good intentions,
但他们觉得这地方是个大麻烦
thinks this place is a large nuisance as it is.
- 一个婴儿  - 你说他活不长了
- A baby... - You said he don't have long.
Queenie 有些生物注定无法生存
Queenie, some creatures aren't meant to survive.
不 这个婴儿 是个奇迹 这是肯定的
No, this baby, he is a miracle. That's for certain.
只是他不是大家期盼的那种奇迹
Just not the kind of miracle one hopes to see.
大家听着 听好了
Y'all listen. Y'all listen up here.
我们有位客人
We're gonna have us a visitor
要和我们住一段时间
that's gonna be staying with us for a little while.
我姐姐生了个小孩 可是她不能抚养 所以
My sister had a child and she couldn't see right by it, so...
他叫
He's known as...
Benjamin
Benjamin.
他的身体不好
He's not a well child,
所以我们要好好照顾他
so we're gonna have to take good care of him.
我生了10个孩子
I had 10 children.
没有孩子照顾不好的 让我看看他
There's not a baby I can't care for. Let me see him.
我的天哪 他长得真像我前夫
God in Heaven. He looks just like my ex-husband.
是这样的 他过早衰老
Look, he's prematurely old.
Rose医生说他活不了多久了
Dr. Rose said he ain't got much more time on this earth.
我们也一样
Join the club.
他在笑呢
He's smiling!
Hambert让我替他问好
Hambert sends his remembrances to you.
你是不是疯了
Are you right out of your mind?
我知道
I know you ain't got all
你没法有自己的孩子
the parts it takes to make one of your own,
但你也不该收养他
but this ain't yours to keep.
他也许都不是人类
It may not even be humankind.
Weathers先生 回来
Mr. Weathers, come back here.
拜托了
Please.
世事难料
You never know what's coming for you.
看样子 我找到了归宿
It seemed I had found a home.
这个故事是真的吗
ls any of this true?
你的声音真好听
You have such a lovely voice.
妈 这是张旧电车票
Mom, it's an ancient streetcar token.
那座钟一直走着
That clock just kept going,
年复一年
year after year after year.
但我不知道我是个孩子
But I didn't know I was a child.
每天都是这些乱七八糟的
Same old crap every day.
我以为我跟这些人一样
I thought I was like everyone else there.
是一个迟暮的老人
An old man in the twilight of his life.
你能让他别玩了吗
Could you make him stop that?
不要再敲叉子了
Stop banging that fork.
叉子是用来吃饭的 不是用来玩的
It's used for eating, not for playing with.
还有 戴好你的餐巾 好吗 Benjamin先生
And use your napkin, please, Mr. Benjamin.
Queenie
Queenie!
看着点 小子
Hey, boy.
我总是有很强的好奇心
Always had a healthy curiosity.
街上是什么样的 下个路口是什么样的
What was up the street? Or around the next corner?
抓住他
Go get him!
Benjamin 这样很危险 赶紧回来
Benjamin! That is dangerous. Come back over here.
别乱跑 孩子
Stay put, child.
我很爱她
I loved her very much.
她是我的母亲
She was my mother.
妈妈
Mama.
有时候 我会觉得我跟前一天有所不同
Some days I feel different than the day before.
每个人对自己的感受都不同 不管是哪方面
Everybody feels different about themselves, one way or another.
但我们都要去向同一个地方
But we're all going the same way.
只是选择了不同的路 就是这样
Just taking different roads to get there, that's all.
你走好自己的路 Benjamin
You're on your own road, Benjamin.
妈妈 我还能活多久
Mama? How much longer I got?
只要对你的所得心怀感激就行 明白吗
Just be thankful for what you're given, hear?
你已经比预想的活得长了
You're already here longer than you're supposed to.
有些夜晚 我得独自睡觉
Some nights, I'd have to sleep alone.
不过我不介意
I didn't mind.
我会聆听房子里的声音
I would listen to the house breathing.
所有人都已入睡
All those people sleeping.
我很有安全感
I felt safe.
那里的生活很有规律
It was a place of great routine.
不管天气如何 每天早晨5点半
Every morning at 5:30, no matter the weather,
退伍的美军Winslow将军都会升旗
General Winslow, U. S. Army, Retired, would raise the flag.
小有名气的前歌剧家Sybil Wagner太太
Mrs. Sybil Wagner, once an opera singer of some note,
会唱Wagner的歌剧
well, she sang Wagner.
Wagner 德国歌剧家
好了 宝贝 来
All right, baby, come on.
我们得给你这对老腿增添点活力
We got to put some life into these old sticks for you.
你能走路的话
Get you walking so you can
就能帮我分担事情了 来 明白吗
help me out around here. Come on now, hear?
不管何季 晚餐总是在5点半准时开始
No matter the season, supper was served promptly at 5:30.
坛浆
Molasses.
糖浆
我5岁开始学习阅读
I learned to read when I was five.
我爷爷是个著名演员的服装师
My grandfather was a dresser for a famous actor.
他会把所有剧本带回家让我读
He brung home every play for me to read.
"我这苟延残喘之人的善良的看守者们
"Kind keepers of my weak decaying age,
出自莎士比亚<亨利六世>上篇第二幕
让垂死的Mortimer在此歇息一下吧
Let dying Mortimer here rest himself.
长期监禁让我的四肢痛苦不堪
Even like a man new haled from the rack,
如同刚被从刑架上拖下来一般
So fare my limbs with long imprisonment.
这灰白的发丝和对死亡的追随
And these gray locks, the pursuivants of death,
预示着Edmund Mortimer的死期即将来临"
Argue the end of Edmund Mortimer."
你是不是以为我什么都不懂
You thought I was plain ignorant, didn't you?
我爷爷是为John Wilkes Booth工作的
The actor my grandfather worked for was John Wilkes Booth.
就是这个人暗杀了林肯
He killed Abraham Lincoln.
世事难料
You never know what's coming for you.
周六晚上 妈妈会带我去教堂
On Saturday nights, Mama would make me go to church.
Benjamin
Benjamin!
用信仰治愈
- 阿门 阿门  - 阿门 阿门
- Amen! Amen! - Amen! Amen!
我能为你做什么呢 小姐
What can I do for you, sister?
她的器官天生有恙
Her parts are all twisted up inside
因此不能生育
and she can't have little children.
主啊 如果你能看清一切 原谅这个女人的罪孽
Lord, if you could see clear to forgive this woman her sins
请让她能够生儿育女
so she can bear the fruit of the womb.
走远吧 你这可恶的折磨
Out, damnable affliction!
- 歌颂上帝  - 歌颂上帝
- Praise God! - Praise God!
哈利路亚
Hallelujah!
- 哈利路亚  - 哈利路亚
- Hallelujah! - Hallelujah!
这位老人有什么病痛呢
And what's this old man's irrediction?
魔鬼缠上了他
He's got the Devil on his back,
想提早把他带入坟墓
trying to ride him into the grave before his time.
- 走远吧 恶魔  - 走远
- Out, Zebuchar! - Yes!
- 走远吧 堕落天使  - 走远
- Out, Beelzebub! - Yes!
你多大了
How old are you?
七岁 但我看起来老很多
Seven. But I look a lot older.
上帝保佑
God bless you.
他才七岁
He's seven.
这是一个乐观向上的人
Now, this is a man with optimism in his heart.
- 没错  - 灵魂镌刻着信仰的人
- All right. - Belief in his soul!
是的 是的
'Yes! 'Yes!
我们在上帝眼中都是孩子
We are all children in the eyes of God!
- 是啊  - 哈里路亚
- Yes! - Hallelujah!
我们要把你从轮椅中解放出来
We are gonna get you out of that chair.
- 我们要让你用双脚走路  - 阿门
- And we're gonna have you walk. - Amen.
没事的
It's all right.
以上帝荣耀之名
In the name of God's glory...
站起来吧
Rise up!
加油
Come on.
快 走走
Come on. Walk.
加油 孩子 快点
Come on, son. Come on.
- 加油试试 孩子  - 加油
- Come on with it, son. Come on. - Come on.
上帝会一路看着你的
Now God is gonna see you the rest of the way.
他会看到这个小老头
He's gonna see this little old
不用拐杖也能走下去
man walk without the use of a crutch or a cane.
他会看到你靠着信仰
He's gonna see that you walk from faith...
- 哈里路亚  - 和神灵的鼓舞独自走下去
- Hallelujah! -...and divine inspiration alone!
- 太好了  - 嘿 Ben
- Yes. - Hey, Ben!
- 走吧 孩子  - 走走看
- Go, son! - Now walk.
- 就这样  - 走
- Yes. - Come on.
别碰他
Don't touch him.
站起来 小老头
Rise up, old man.
像Lazarus一样站起来
Rise up like Lazarus.
Lazarus死亡后 耶稣一口断定他将复活 四天后Lazarus果然复活了
我说 站起来
I said, rise up!
哈里路亚
Hallelujah!
就是这样
Yes.
加油
Come on.
说哈里路亚
Say hallelujah.
- 哈里路亚  - 哈里路亚
- Hallelujah! - Hallelujah!
走
Walk.
接着走 没错
Walk on. Yes.
就是这样 Benjamin
That's right, Benjamin.
现在回想起来 那的确是个奇迹
Now when I look back on it, it was miraculous.
但你知道这样一句话
But you know the saying,
有所得 必有所失
the Lord giveth and the Lord taketh away.
向主致以最崇高的敬意
Glory in the highest!
天啊
Sweet Jesus!
- 不要啊  - 不要
- No! - No!
这里有很多人过生日
There were so many birthdays.
他是个快乐的好伙伴 他是个快乐的好伙伴
For he's a jolly good fellow For he's a jolly good fellow...
我们的蜡烛用不完 因为我们都省着用
So we wouldn't run out, we would spare the candles.
Queenie 你知道我就不喜欢过生日也不喜欢吃蛋糕
Queenie, you know I don't like birthdays and I don't like cake.
死神是这里的常客 有人来 有人去
And death was a common visitor. People came and went.
有人离开时 你总能感觉到
You always knew when someone left us.
那时的房子寂静无声
There was a silence in the house.
这是适合成长的好地方
It was a wonderful place to grow up.
我身边的人
I was with people who had
都抛开了过往生活的矛盾
shed all the inconsequences of earlier life.
只关心天气 洗澡水的温度
Left wondering about the weather, the temperature of a bath,
和一天将要结束时的阳光
the light at the end of a day.
总会有人来填补那些死者的房间
For everyone that died, someone would come to take their place.
我结了五次婚
I've been married five times.
我和我的第五任妻子
My fifth wife and I are
被附近的食人族部落抓住了
captured by a neighbor tribe of cannibals.
哦 天呐
Oh, goodness gracious.
我们跨过河流逃跑
We escaped across the river.
我妻子不会游泳 很不幸 她被吃了
My wife, she can't swim, so, sadly, she eaten.
我的天
Oh, my God.
我第二任妻子踩到毒蛇 也死了
My second wife steps on cobra and dies.
和我结婚 真的很晦气
It was very bad luck to be married to me.
那是Oti先生 他是我一熟人的熟人
That's Mr. Oti. He's an acquaintance of an acquaintance of mine.
- 第二年夏天 我和我的  - 他是俾格米人
- The next summer I'm captured... - He's a Pygmy.
身高不满5英尺(约1.5米)的矮小人种
其他三位妻子被抓到巴齐里部落
...with three others by the Baschiele tribe.
他们用我们 跟一个陌生美国人
They trade us for pigs, shoes,
交换猪 鞋子 和啤酒
and beer to a very strange American man.
我听说 你没有看起来的那么老
I hear you're not so old as you're looking.
你骗了所有人
You just fooling everybody.
怎么回事 感染了马甲本吗
What's the matter? Did you get Madjembe?
马甲本是什么
What's Madjembe?
虫子
Worms.
我觉得不是虫子
I don't think I have worms.
我天生就这样
This is just how I am.
走吧 一起喝杯根汁汽水
Come. Let's get a cold root beer.
我在你枕头下面发现了药哦
I found the medication under your pillow.
我不能喝的 太危险了
I'm not supposed to. It's dangerous.
谁说危险的 走吧 小老头
Who said that? Come on, little man.
孩子们好
Hello, children.
麻烦停车
Hold, please.
后来我在费城动物园的猴馆里
Then I'm in the monkey house at Philadelphia Zoological Park.
第一天就有三千个人来看我
Three thousand people show up my first day.
你看
Look.
布须曼人与猩猩
同住笼中
住在笼子里什么感觉
What's it like living in a cage?
特别臭
It stinks.
但是那些猴子
But the monkeys.
它们会玩些小把戏
They do some tricks there.
我丢长矛 和Kowali摔角
I throw a spear, wrestle with Kowali.
她是只红毛猩猩
She is orangutan.
我不跟猴子们玩儿的时候
When I'm not playing with the monkeys,
他们就要我张牙舞爪地
they want me to run to the bars
冲到我的铁笼前
in my cage, with my teeth.
后来你做了什么
So then what'd you do?
我离开了动物园 到处闯荡 多半时间都在闲逛
Then I leave zoo, go here, go there. Wandered most of the time.
就你一个人
You were all alone?
大多数时间你都是孤单的
Plenty of time you'll be alone.
我们这些异类 都是这样
When you're different like us, it's gonna be that way.
但告诉你个秘密
But I'll tell you a little secret.
人类 不管是高矮胖瘦
Fat people, skinny people, tall people,
还是白人 他们和我们一样孤单
white people, they're just as alone as we are.
不同的是 他们怕得要死
But they're scared shitless.
我想念我长大的那条河
I think about the river I grew up on.
如果能再坐在河边 一定很美好
It would be nice to sit by my river again.
来 我要去赴约了
Come, I have an appointment.
你终于来啦 准备好了吗 亲爱的
There's my little man. You ready, sugar?
时刻准备着
Always ready. Always ready.
Filamena 这是Benjamin先生
Filamena, Mr. Benjamin.
- 见到你很高兴 先生  - 我的荣幸 女士
- It's a pleasure to meet you, sir. - My pleasure, ma'am.
你可以自己回家的 对吧
You can find your own way home, can't you?
坐圣查尔斯线到拿破仑站
Take the St. Charles line to Napoleon.
嘿 嘿
Hey! Hey!
天呐 你去哪儿了 赶紧进来
Where in God's name have you been? Get in here.
我都快担心死了 知道吗
I mean, you take my breath away, you know that?
天呐 我太担心你了
Oh, Lord, I was so worried about you.
那是我人生中最美好的一天
It had been the best day of my life.
- 她的呼吸怎么样了  - 很微弱
- How's her breathing? -It's shallow.
他们说飓风几小时内就会来了
They say it'll reach us in a few hours,
我得把我儿子带到我姐姐那里去
so I gotta get my baby and take him to my sister's.
他们说医院这边没什么好担心的
They say there's nothing to worry about here in the hospital.
如果需要帮助 护士就在这里 你还好吗
Nurses'll be right here if you need them. Are you okay?
- 没事 我读日记呢  - 一小时内我就回来
- Yeah, I'm okay reading. - I shouldn't be more than an hour.
有人来陪了吗
Was there just company?
是Dorothy要走了
It was just Dorothy leaving.
继续读吧 Caroline
Go on, Caroline.
"到了周日 家人们会来探望"
"On Sundays, the families would come and visit."
那是1930年的感恩节
It was Thanksgiving, 1930.
我遇见了改变了我一生的人
I met the person who changed my life forever.
哇 Benjamin
Well, Benjamin.
你看起来真是太年轻了啊
Might I say you are looking strikingly youthful.
你好 Fuller太太
Good day, Mrs. Fuller.
现在用一根拐杖 背也挺得笔直
A single cane, back straight as an arrow.
你吃了什么灵丹妙药啊
What elixir have you been drinking?
- 谢谢夸奖 女士  - 奶奶 看我
- Thank you, ma'am. - Grandma! Look at me!
跳得真好
That was really something.
快过来
Come on over here, you.
这是我孙女 Daisy
Now, this is my granddaughter, Daisy.
这是
This is Mr...
抱歉 Benjamin 我还不知道你姓什么
I'm afraid, Benjamin, I don't rightly know your last name.
叫我Benjamin就行了
Benjamin's fine.
我永远不会忘记她那双蓝眼睛
I never forgot her blue eyes.
各位 晚餐已经好了
Good people, supper is served.
为了健康和食物 爱情和友谊
Health and food, for love and friends.
为了上帝恩赐的一切
For everything thy goodness sends.
阿门
Amen.
- 阿门  - 阿门
- Amen! - Amen!
你知道吗 火鸡其实不算鸟类
Did you know turkeys aren't really birds?
为什么呢
Why do you say that?
它们属于雉科 它们不会飞
They're in the pheasant family, can't hardly fly.
真可悲 对吧 不会飞的鸟
It's sad, don't you think? Birds that can't fly?
我喜欢不会飞的鸟
I love birds that can't fly.
它们是人间美味
They are so delicious.
- 你太坏了  - 在我们感谢主的恩赐时
- That's terrible. - I have something to tell y'all
我想告诉你们一件事
while we're giving thanks for God's blessings.
奇迹降临在我身上了
I had a miracle happen.
主竟然回应了我的祈祷
The Lord saw fit to answer my prayers.
什么意思 回应了什么祈祷
What does she mean, answered her prayers?
谢谢 谢谢
Thanks. Thank you.
笨蛋 她有孩子了
She's gonna have a baby, silly.
我妈妈怀上我弟弟的时候就是这么说的
That's what my mama said when I was gonna have a baby brother,
可惜他命不长
but he didn't live long,
因为他的呼吸有问题
'cause he didn't breathe right.
"下午 他长出了健壮漂亮的后腿
"In the afternoon, when he had got his beautiful hind legs
正如大神农答应的一般
Just as Big God Nqong had promised.
那时是5点
You can see that it is 5:00,
大神农的钟表上就是这么显示的"
Because Big God Nqong's clock says so."
很厉害吧
Isn't that something?
再讲一遍嘛
Again, read it again.
是啊 再讲一遍嘛
Oh, read it again, please.
好 但是听完之后 你必须去睡觉
All right. But afterwards, you must go to bed.
我保证
I promise.
"老袋鼠"
"Old Man Kangaroo."
你睡着了吗
Are you sleeping?
是谁啊
Who's that?
我啊 Daisy
It's me, Daisy.
哦 嗨
Oh, hi!
跟我来
'Kay, come on.
我们去哪儿
Where are we going?
快点 到这下面来
Come on. Under here.
你来点着
Here, you light it.
我不能玩火柴的
I'm not supposed to play with matches.
不要那么胆小 快点着
Don't be a chicken. Light it.
如果你告诉我一个秘密 我也告诉你一个
I'll tell you a secret if you'll tell me one.
好
Okay.
我看见我妈妈亲了另一个男人
I saw my mama kissing another man.
她的脸都红了
Her face was red from it.
该你了
Your turn.
我没有看上去的那么老
I'm not as old as I look.
我也这么觉得
I thought so.
你不像个老人
You don't seem like an old person.
- 像我奶奶一样  - 是的
- Like my grandma. - I'm not.
你生病了吗
Are you sick?
我听我妈妈跟Tizzy窃窃私语
Well, I heard Mama and Tizzy whispering.
他们说我命不久矣 但可能又不是
They said I was gonna die soon, but maybe not.
你真奇怪
You're odd.
你跟我见过的其他人都不一样
You're different than anybody I've ever met.
- 可以摸一下吗  - 好
- May I? - Okay.
你们在这下面干什么
What are you doing under there?
你给我出来 回床上睡觉去
You come right out here and get back up to bed!
这都大半夜了
It's after midnight!
你们不能再一起玩了
You are not to be playing together.
知道了 女士
Yes, ma'am.
赶紧回床上 小姑娘
Now you get back to bed, little lady.
你太小了 大晚上的不能一个人乱跑
You're too young to be wandering around in the night on your own.
你真应该为自己感到羞耻
And you ought to be ashamed of yourself.
你是个与众不同的孩子
You are a different child.
你是老孩子
A man-child.
孩子 其他人
And, baby, people aren't
是不会理解你的与众不同的
gonna understand just how different you are.
我究竟有什么病 妈妈
What's wrong with me, Mama?
过来
Come here.
上帝也没有告诉我 孩子
God hasn't said yet, baby.
回床上吧 好吗 管好自己
Now go on to bed, hear? And behave yourself.
去吧 记得祈祷 听见了吗
Go on. Say your prayers, hear?
我有没有告诉过你 我曾被闪电击中了7次
Did I ever tell you I've been struck by lightning seven times?
一次是我在修补屋顶
Once when I was repairing a leak on the roof.
一次是过马路去取信
Once I was just crossing the road to get the mail.
我永远不会忘记她的
I never forgot her...
"蓝眼睛"
"...blue eyes."
妈
Mom?
你明白这个Benjamin
Did you get that this Benjamin
是对你一见钟情吗
loved you from the first time that he saw you?
并不是谁都有这样的经历
Not many people experience that.
想让我继续读吗
Want me to go on?
他划掉了一些话
He crosses something out.
那婴儿出生之后 一切都变了
When that baby came, things were different.
*妈咪要离开 爹地不会走*
*Your mama gone away and your daddy gonna stay*
*谁都不会抛下你*
*Didn't leave nobody but the baby*
有人出生 也有人死亡
Babies were born, people died.
许多人进出过那所老房子
A lot of folks been through that old house.
我是来道别的 我要走了
I've come to say goodbye. I'm going away.
走了
Going?
去哪儿
Where?
我还没想好
I haven't figured that out yet,
但我到了那里会给你寄明信片的
but I'll send you a postcard when I get there.
你朋友呢 高个子的那个女士
What about your friend, the tall lady?
我们不再是朋友了
We are not friends anymore.
和高个子在一起就是会这样
That's what happens with tall people sometimes.
好吧 再见了
Well, goodbye.
那一年 我一个人度过了大部分的时光
Spent a lot of time by myself that year.
有人吗
Hello?
- 嗨  - 我是今天搬进来的
- Hi. - I'm moving in today.
欢迎 我们一直等你呢
Welcome. We've been expecting you.
你能带她去Rousseau太太以前的房间吗
Can you please show her up to Mrs. Rousseau's old room?
抱歉 我们一般不允许狗进房子的
I'm sorry, but we usually don't allow dogs in the house.
她已经很老了 也瞎得差不多了
Well, she's old as the hills. She's almost blind.
不会麻烦你们很久的
She won't be a bother much longer.
好吧 只要不碍事 待多久都行
Well, all right, long as she stays from up underfoot.
这边请 女士
Right this way, ma'am.
尽管我努力回忆 我也想不起她的名字
As hard as I try, I can't remember her name.
Lawson太太还是Hartford太太
Mrs. Lawson, or Mrs. Hartford.
也许是Maple
Maybe it was Maple.
有趣的是 有时候我们最记不起的人
It's funny how sometimes the people we remember the least
却给我们留下最深刻的印象
make the greatest impression on us.
不过我记得她戴着钻戒
I do remember she wore diamonds.
总是打扮得很漂亮 像是要出门一样
And she always dressed in fine clothing, as if she was going out.
尽管她从不出门 也没人来看望她
Although she never did and nobody ever came to visit her.
她教我弹钢琴
She taught me to play the piano.
弹得好不好不重要
It's not about how well you play.
重要的是你对所弹曲子的感受
It's how you feel about what you're playing.
试试这首
Try this.
你会情不自禁沉浸在曲子中
You can't help putting yourself in the music.
变化总在发生
There were many changes.
有些你能看得到 有些看不到
Some you could see, some you couldn't.
比如毛发开始生长了
Hair had started growing in all sorts of places,
还有其他的也开始生长了
along with other things.
这让我感觉很好
I felt pretty good, considering.
亲爱的 疼
Darling, the pain.
好 妈妈 我去叫护士
All right, Mom, I'll get the nurse.
看风暴中心 这是强烈飓风
Look at this eye. This is a major hurricane,
移动缓慢 但伴随着最大持续风速
a slow hurricane, with maximum sustained winds of...
感觉不太好吗
Not doing too good?
看来没人知道到底是走是留
Nobody seems to know whether to stay or leave.
我就打算待在这里了
I'm gonna ride it out.
好了 这样会让你舒服很多
There. That should make things much easier.
你有机会道别了吗
Have you had a chance to say your goodbyes?
我爸爸等我哥哥
My father waited four hours
从伯格赶来等了四个小时
for my brother to get here from Boger City.
不愿意走的时候没有他的陪伴
Couldn't go without him.
- 她看着是个好人  - 是啊
- She seems like a sweet woman. - Yeah.
可惜我没有很多时间陪她
I haven't had as much time with her as I would've...
- 忙吗 麻烦帮我个忙  - 失陪了
- You busy? I could use your help. - Excuse me.
没事
Sure.
"Queenie会让我跟Daws先生一起"
"Queenie would let me go with Mr. Daws..."
去波弗蒂角看船随波逐流
...to Poverty Point to watch the boats go up and down the river.
这段日子不好过
These were hard times.
我有没有告诉过你 我曾被闪电击中了7次
Did I ever tell you I was struck by lightning seven times?
有一次是我在田里放牛
Once when I was in the field, just tending to my cows.
我的下手没来
My fourth hand didn't show up.
有人想在这儿打工赚个两块钱吗
Anybody want to make $2 for a day's work 'round here?
怎么回事
What's the matter?
没人想老实工作赚点工钱吗
Nobody wants to do an honest day's work for an honest day's pay?
他从来不付工资
He never pays.
- 没人想要工作吗  - 我想
- Nobody wants a job? - I do.
你不晕船吗 老头
You got your sea legs about you, old man?
应该吧
I think.
这就够了
Well, that's good enough for me.
赶紧上船 上来就知道了
Get your ass on board. We'll sure as hell find out.
切 尔 西 号
新奥尔良
我从没这么开心过
I was as happy as I could be.
我需要个人手
I need a volunteer!
我什么都愿意做
I would do anything.
我来 船长
Yes, Captain!
把这些鸟屎清干净
Scrape off all this bird shit!
这就做 先生
Right away, sir.
事实上 我还拿到了
And I was actually gonna be paid for something
本来拿不到的报酬
I would've done for free.
他是Mike Clark船长
His name was Captain Mike Clark.
他7岁起就在拖船上了
He'd been on a tugboat since he was seven.
快上来
Get moving, then.
过来
Come here.
你现在还能勃起吗
Can you still get it up?
每天早上都会
I do every morning.
就你这老屌 能挺得又高又硬
The old pole, huh? The high, hard one?
是的吧
I guess.
你上一次碰女人是什么时候
When was the last time you had a woman?
- 从没碰过  - 从没有
- Never. - Never?
我记得没有 先生
Not that I know of, sir.
你等等
Wait a minute, now.
你是说 你活了这么多年
You mean to say you've been on this earth however many years
还没碰过女人
and you've never had a woman?
老天 这是我听过的最悲哀的事情了
Damn, that's the saddest thing I've ever heard in my life.
从没碰过吗
Never?
从没有
No.
老天爷 你一定得跟我走
Well, then, by Jesus, you are coming with me.
你爸爸是做什么的
What did your father do?
我从没见过他
I never met my father.
你个幸运的王八蛋
You lucky bastard.
所有父亲想做的就是压制你
All fathers want to do is hold you down.
我在我父亲的船上 日夜做工
Out on my father's boat, workin' the two-a-day,
这个矮胖子
this little, fat bastard.
他们叫他"拖船爱尔兰佬"
"Tug Irish," They called him.
最后 我终于鼓起勇气告诉他
Anyway, I finally work up the nerve and tell him,
"我可不想把我剩下的时光都浪费在这破船上"
"I don't want to spend the rest of my life on a goddamn tugboat."
知道我的意思吗
You know what I'm saying?
你不想把你剩下的时光都浪费在破船上
You don't want to spend the rest of your life on a tugboat.
没错 就是这样
Absolutely! Damn right!
你知道我爸对我说什么吗
So you know what my father says to me?
他说"你他妈算哪根葱"
He says, "Who the hell do you think you are?
"你他妈以为你能做什么"
"What the hell do you think you can do?"
我跟他说
So I tell him.
"既然你问了 那我就告诉你
"Well, if you're asking,
我想成为艺术家"
I want to be an artist."
他笑了
He laughs.
"艺术家 你命中注定要在拖船上工作 就像我一样
"An artist? God meant for you to work a tugboat, just like me.
这就是你的工作"
And that's exactly what you're gonna do."
但我还是成为了一名艺术家
Well, I turned myself into an artist.
一名纹身师
A tattoo artist!
每一个纹身都是我自己纹的
I put on every one of these myself.
你得把我活剥了才能让艺术脱离我
You have to skin me alive to take my art away from me now.
我死了之后 要给我爸寄一只胳膊
When I'm dead, I'm gonna send him my arm.
这一只
That one.
别让别人对你指指点点
Don't let anyone tell you different.
要去做命中注定的事
You gotta do what you're meant to do.
而我注定去做一名艺术家
And I happen to be a goddamned artist.
但你现在是个船长
But you're a tugboat captain.
Mike船长
Captain Mike?
我们为你和你的朋友准备好了
We're ready for you and your friend.
走吧 老头 破了你的处
Let's go, old timer, eh? Break your cherry.
- 你们好 小可爱们  - 嘿 船长
- Hello, my lovelies! - Hey, Captain.
- 你好船长  - 你好
- Hi, Captain. - Hi.
- 你好  - 你好
- Hi. - Hi.
他搞得我心里发毛 我不要他
He gives me the willies. That is not for me.
你今晚过得好吗 老爷爷
How are you tonight, grandpa?
那是一个难忘的夜晚
It was a night to remember.
你是至尊"屌"探还是什么吗 我要休息了
What are you, Dick Tracy or something? I've got to rest.
再来一次
Again.
- 谢谢  - 应该谢谢你 今晚过得很好
- Thank you. - No, thank you. You have a nice night.
- 你明天还在吗  - 我每晚都在 除了周日
- Will you be here tomorrow? - Every night but Sunday.
这让我明白了谋生的意义
It sure made me understand the value of earning a living.
晚安 亲爱的 快点回来
Good night, sweetie. Come back now.
钱能买到的东西
Things money can buy you.
外面太脏了
It's nasty out.
让我送你一程吧
Can I offer you a ride somewhere?
你太善良了 先生
Well, that's awfully kind of you, sir.
我叫Thomas Thomas Button
My name is Thomas, Thomas Button.
- 我叫Benjamin  - Benjamin
- I'm Benjamin. - Benjamin.
认识你很高兴
It's a pleasure to know you.
你想去哪里喝一杯吗
Would you like to stop somewhere and have a drink?
好啊
All right.
晚上好 Button先生
Evening, Mr. Button.
先生要喝什么
What'll it be, sir?
- 跟他的一样吧  - 我俩都要萨泽拉克
- I'll have whatever he's having. - Sazerac for the both of us.
加威士忌 不要白兰地
With whiskey, not brandy.
你不喝酒 对吗
You don't drink, do you?
- 这是我的第一次之夜  - 怎么说
- It's a night for firsts. - How's that?
我之前也从没去过妓院
I've never been to a brothel, either.
这是段经历
Well, it's an experience.
没错 凡是总有第一次
It certainly is. There's a time for everything.
- 说得对  - 你们的酒
- True enough. - Your drinks.
无意冒犯 你的手 疼吗
I don't mean to be rude, but your hands. Is that painful?
我天生就有些疾病
Well, I was born with some form of disease.
什么疾病
What kind of disease?
我生下来就是老人
I was born old.
- 很抱歉  - 没必要的
- I'm sorry. - No need to be.
年纪大没有错
There's nothing wrong with old age.
我妻子几年前去世了
My wife passed away many years ago.
很遗憾 抱歉
I'm so, so sorry.
她在分娩时死了
She died in childbirth.
- 敬孩子  - 敬母亲
- To children. - To mothers.
你做什么工作的 Button先生
What line of work you in, Mr. Button?
纽扣生意 Button纽扣公司
Buttons. Button's Buttons.
什么纽扣我们都做
There isn't a button that we don't make.
我最大的竞争对手是B.F.Goodrich
Our biggest competition is B. F. Goodrich
和他的破拉链企业
and his infernal zippers.
你们还要喝点什么吗
Would you gentlemen like anything else?
临走前再喝一杯 Benjamin
One for the road, Benjamin?
除非让我来请 Button先生
Only if you let me pay for it, Mr. Button.
那你是做什么工作的
So, what line of work do you do?
我在拖船上工作
I'm a tugboat man.
我喜欢和你聊天
I enjoyed talking to you.
我喜欢和你喝酒
I enjoyed drinking with you.
Benjamin
Benjamin?
你介意我偶尔过来看看你吗
Would you mind if, time to time, I stopped by and said hello?
随时都可以 晚安 Button先生
Anytime. Good night, Mr. Button.
晚安 Benjamin
Good night, Benjamin.
走吧
Drive on.
你去哪儿了
Where have you been?
没什么 我去见了些人 听了听音乐
Nothing. I met some people and listened to some music.
哦 天呐 孩子
Oh, sweet Jesus, boy!
长大是件趣事 它会悄悄接近你
Growing up's a funny thing. Sneaks up on you.
本来是一个人
One person is there,
突然就长大成了另外一个人
then suddenly somebody else has taken her place.
她不再是原来的样子了
She wasn't all elbows and knees anymore.
Benjamin 快来
Benjamin! Come on!
好
Okay.
我喜欢她来这里
I loved those weekends when she'd come
陪她奶奶的那些周末
and spend the night with her grandmother.
Daisy Daisy
Daisy. Daisy.
你想看个东西吗
You want to see something?
你要保密
You gotta keep it a secret,
穿好衣服 我们在外面见
so get dressed. I'll meet you out back.
快来
Come on.
- 你会游泳吗  - 你会的我都会
- Can you swim? - I can do anything you can do.
来 把这个穿好 我们得快点了
Here, put this on. We gotta hurry.
他还好吗
Is he okay?
船长
Captain?
Mike船长
Captain Mike?
早上好 船长 能带我们出去吗
Morning, Captain. Can you take us out?
你知道今天是什么日子吗
Do you know what day it is?
周日
Sunday?
知道周日是什么意思吗
Do you know what that means?
意思是我昨晚喝得烂醉
Means I was very drunk last night.
你每天都喝得烂醉
Well, you're drunk every night.
- 那是个姑娘  - 好朋友
- Is that a girl? - Close friend.
我想带她看看河
I want to show her the river.
你不能跟外人去兜风的
You're not supposed to go joyriding with civilians.
我会丢了我的执照的
I could lose my license.
你在等什么呢
What are you waiting for?
靠岸修一下帆布
Pulled in for repair a wounded duck.
她都在飞了 哈
She's flying now, huh?
嘿 水手
Ahoy, sailor!
真希望我们能跟他们一起远行
I wish we could go with them.
你说什么了 妈妈
Did you say something, Mom?
天气越来越不好了
It's getting really bad.
能听见我声音吗 妈妈
Can you hear me, Mom?
我没多少时间了
Time just seeped out of me.
"世事变化飞快"
"Things were changing quickly."
我不知道怎么回事 但你好像头发更多了
I don't know how it's possible, but you seem to have more hair.
如果我告诉你我没有越来越老
What if I told you that I wasn't getting older,
而是比别人越来越年轻了呢
but I was getting younger than everybody else?
那我为你感到抱歉
Well, I'd feel sorry for you,
因为你会看着你爱的人在你之前死去
to have to see everybody you love die before you do.
这是份可怕的责任
It's an awful responsibility.
我从没有从那个角度思考过人生和死亡
I'd never thought about life or death that way before.
Benjamin 我们注定要失去我们爱的人
Benjamin, we're meant to lose the people we love.
不然怎么能知道他们对我们有多重要呢
How else would we know how important they are to us?
秋季的一天 一个熟客来敲开了我们的门
And one fall day, a familiar visitor came knocking on our door.
你想跟我一起去药店吗
You want to go with me to the drugstore?
她教我怎么弹钢琴
She taught me how to play the piano.
- 阿门  - 阿门
- Amen. - Amen.
她教我思念是什么感觉
And she taught me what it meant to miss somebody.
我们走吧
Let's go.
我去了妓院
I had gone to a brothel.
我喝了人生第一杯酒
I'd had my first drink.
跟一个朋友说了永别然后埋葬了另一个朋友
Said goodbye to one friend and buried another.
1936年
In 1936, when I was coming
我快18岁的时候
to the end of the 17th year of my life,
我收起行囊 道了再见
I packed my bag, said goodbye.
- 再见 Benjamin  - 再见
- Bye, Benjamin. - Goodbye.
生活如果还是这样
I knew, life being what it was,
我可能再也见不到他们了
I'd probably never see them again.
再见 Benjamin先生
Bye, Mr. Benjamin.
- 孩子 祝你好运  - 谢谢
- Good luck to you, son. - Thank you.
- 我爱你 妈妈  - 我也爱你 孩子
- I love you, Mama. - I love you, too, baby.
记得每晚都要祷告 知道吗
I want you to say your prayers every night, hear?
注意安全
Be safe, hear?
Benjamin
Benjamin!
- 你要去哪儿  - 海上
- Where you going? - To sea.
我会给你寄明信片的
I'll send you a postcard.
无论在哪里
From everywhere.
无论在哪里 都要给我寄明信片
Write me a postcard from everywhere.
你能想象吗
Can you imagine?
他会从他去过的每个地方寄明信片给我
He sent me a postcard from everywhere he went.
每个他工作过的地方
Every place he worked.
纽芬兰 巴芬湾
Newfoundland. Baffin Bay.
格拉斯哥 利物浦 纳尔维克
Glasgow. Liverpool. Narvik.
他和那个Mike船长远走了
He had gone with that Captain Mike.
Mike船长和Moran兄弟拖船海上救助公司
Captain Mike had contracted for three years
签了三年的合同
with Moran Brothers Tug and Salvage.
那艘旧船
The old ship had been refitted
用柴油机和绞车改装过
with a diesel engine and a new sea winch.
我们绕过佛罗里达 沿着大西洋海岸航行
We went around Florida and up the Atlantic seaboard.
船上有7名船员 Mike船长和我
We were a crew of seven now. Captain Mike and me.
厨师 来自特拉华州威尔明顿市的Prentiss Mayes
Cookie, Prentiss Mayes from Wilmington, Delaware.
Brody双胞胎 Rick和Vic
The Brody twins, Rick and Vic,
他们在海上相处得很好 但不知道为什么
who got along fine at sea but, for some reason,
一回到陆地
once they were on dry land
就互相看不惯了
couldn't stand the sight of each other.
每8艘船中 有1艘船会永远回不来
You know, one in every eight boats never returns.
有个叫John Grimm的人 人如其名
There was John Grimm, who sure fit his name.
所有手下在海上失踪了
All hands lost at sea.
来自南达科他州的贝尔维迪尔
From Belvedere, South Dakota.
还有来自北卡罗来纳州山区阿什维尔的Pleasant Curtis
And Pleasant Curtis from Asheville, Notch.
除了自言自语外 从没跟别人说过话
Never said a word to anyone, except himself.
我时常写信给他
I wrote him constantly.
告诉他我受邀参加纽约市
I told him I had been invited to audition in New York City
美国芭蕾舞学院的面试
for the School of American Ballet.
请留下
Please stay.
谢谢 谢谢
Thank you. Thank you.
你可以留下来
You can stay.
但我在团里并不出挑
But I was relegated to the corps.
只是个跳舞的流浪者
Another dancing gypsy.
Benjamin
Benjamin!
第一次见你的时候
How is it when you showed up
你比系船柱大不了多少 还快要进棺材里了
you were no bigger than a bollard with one foot in the grave,
现在 是我喝得太多了
but now, either I drink a hell of a lot more than I think I do,
还是你长高了
or you sprouted?
你有什么秘密
What's your secret?
这个嘛 船长
Well, Captain,
的确是你喝多了
you do drink a lot.
我们住在一个有着恢弘名字的小旅馆里 冬宫
We stayed in a small hotel with a grand name, The Winter Palace.
你根本不知道你在说什么
You have no idea what you're talking about.
蜂鸟可不是一般的鸟
The hummingbird is not just another bird.
它的心率有每分钟1200下
Its heart rate's 1,200 beats per minute.
它的翅膀每秒振动80次
Its wings beat 80 times a second.
要是阻止它扇动翅膀
If you was to stop their wings from beating,
它不到10秒内就会死亡
it would be dead in less than 10 seconds.
它不是一般的鸟
This is no ordinary bird.
它简直就是奇迹
This is a frickin' miracle.
人们用影像放慢翅膀的扇动
They slowed down their wings with moving pictures,
你们猜他们看到了什么
and you know what they saw?
它们的翅尖是这样的
Their wingtips are doing that.
知道数字8有什么数学意义吗
You know what the figure eight is the mathematical symbol for?
无穷大
Infinity.
Infinity!
每个人 不管他们有什么不同
Everybody, no matter what differences they had,
语言也好 肤色也罢 都有一个共同点
the languages, the color of their skin, had one thing in common.
他们每晚都烂醉如泥
They were drunk every single night.
三楼 谢谢
Three, please.
能等一下我们吗 好吗
Could you hold, dear, for us, please?
非常感谢 晚上好
Thank you very much. Good evening.
她叫Elizabeth Abbott
Her name was Elizabeth Abbott.
她不漂亮 简单如纸
She was not beautiful. She was plain as paper.
但是她在我眼里很美
But she was pretty as any picture to me.
你在看什么
What are you looking at?
你要知道 我们有个长期协议
If you must know, we have a longstanding agreement
不醉不归
never to go to bed sober.
- 对吗 亲爱的  - 你说什么就是什么 亲爱的
- Isn't that right, darling? - Whatever you say, darling.
她丈夫叫Walter Abbott
Her husband was Walter Abbott.
他是英国贸易代表团在摩尔曼斯克的首席部长
He was Chief Minister of the British Trade Mission in Murmansk,
他也是个间谍
and he was a spy.
- 亲爱的  - 谢谢 亲爱的
- Darling. - Oh, thank you, my darling.
- 亲爱的 钥匙  - 哦 对
- Key, darling. - Oh, yes.
我的一只鞋跟断了
I broke my heel off one of my shoes.
我可不习惯不穿鞋走路
I'm not in the habit of walking about in my stocking feet.
那里白昼很长
They were long days there.
但黑夜更长
And even longer nights.
有一晚 我失眠了
One particular night, I was having trouble sleeping.
抱歉
I'm sorry.
我睡不着
I couldn't sleep.
我要去泡点茶 你想喝点儿吗
I was gonna make some tea. Would you like some?
不用了 谢谢
Oh, no. Thank you.
加牛奶还是蜂蜜
Milk? Honey?
加点蜂蜜 谢谢
A bit of honey, please.
希望你不介意蜂蜜里有苍蝇
I hope you like flies in your honey.
哦 那还是算了
Oh, perhaps not.
让它多浸一会儿可能会更好
Oh, maybe better to let it steep a little.
浸
Steep?
浸泡
Soak.
我的意思是 泡茶就该用正确的方式
I don't know, I mean, there's a proper way of making tea.
在我家乡 人们只希望它是热的
Well, where I'm from, people just want it to be hot.
对 也没错
Well, quite right.
- 你现在是海员  - 水手
- Now, you're a seaman. - A sailor.
希望你不要觉得我无礼 但我想问
I hope you won't think me impolite, but I have to ask,
你这个年纪当水手不会太老吗
aren't you a little old to be working on a boat?
水手没有年龄限制 只要你能胜任这份工作
There's no age limit, as long as you can do the work.
你失眠吗 谢谢
And you have trouble sleeping? Thank you.
我以前不这样 我一般睡得像婴儿一样沉
I didn't think I did. I usually sleep like a baby.
有些事让我睡不着
Something's been keeping me up.
我爸爸在他80多岁的时候
My father, in his 80s,
深信自己会在睡梦中死去
he was so convinced he was gonna die in his sleep,
他只让自己睡午觉
he limited himself to having afternoon naps.
并坚信自己可以骗过死神
He was so determined he was gonna cheat death.
- 他有吗  - 有什么
- Did he? - Did he what?
在睡梦中死去
Die in his sleep?
他坐在他最爱的椅子上
He died sitting in his favorite chair
听着他最喜欢的广播死去了
listening to his favorite program on the wireless.
他一定预感到了什么
He must have known something.
我丈夫是英国贸易部部长
My husband's the British Trade Minister,
我们来这儿14个月了
and we've been here for 14 months.
- 天啊  - 我们本来要去北京的
- Good God. - We were supposed to go to Peking
但可能永远都去不了了
but it never seemed to work out.
你去过远东吗
Have you been in the Far East?
没有 我哪里都没去过
No. I've never been anywhere, really.
我是说 海港以外的地方
I mean, outside of harbors.
你是哪里来的
And where is it that you're from?
路易斯安那州的新奥尔良
New Orleans. Louisiana.
没有第二个新奥尔良了
I didn't know there was another.
然后她告诉了我
And she told me about all
她去过的所有地方 和她的所见所闻
the places she had been, and what she had seen.
我们一直聊到快天亮
And we talked till just before the dawn.
我自己是个酒鬼
I'm just a lush, myself.
我们回到了各自的房间 过各自的生活
And we went back to our rooms, to our separate lives.
但每天晚上 我们都会在大厅见面
But every night, we'd meet again in that lobby.
午夜时分的旅馆是个神奇的地方
A hotel in the middle of the night can be a magical place.
老鼠跑跑停停
A mouse running, and stopping.
暖气嘶嘶作响
A radiator hissing.
窗帘随风呜鸣
A curtain blowing.
这让人觉得宁静 甚至慰藉
There's something peaceful, even comforting
因为你知道所爱之人在床上熟睡
knowing that the people you love are asleep in their beds
没有什么能伤害他们
where nothing can harm them.
Elizabeth和我会忘记时间
Elizabeth and I would lose track of the night
直到黎明到来
until just before daybreak.
我想我可能让你误解了
I think I may have given you the wrong impression.
什么
Beg pardon?
已婚女人可不会经常在半夜
Well, married women don't customarily sit around
和陌生男人坐在旅馆里
in the middle of the night with strange men in hotels.
我不知道已婚女人该做什么 不该做什么
I wouldn't know what a married woman does or doesn't do.
晚安
Good night.
摩尔曼斯克
Murmansk.
"我遇见了一个人 坠入了爱河"
"I've met somebody, and I've fallen in love."
妈妈
Mom?
那都是60多年前的事了
That was over 60 years ago.
你爱他吗 妈妈
Did you love him, Mother?
小女孩哪懂什么爱情
What does a girl know about love?
呃
Well...
- 我穿得不得体  - 看起来很好啊 这才是你
- I'm not dressed. - Oh, you look splendid, just as you are.
在摩尔曼斯克 不要为
Don't waste any time bothering
红酒或者奶酪而费心
about the wine or the cheese in Murmansk,
因为那些实在很平常
'cause they're really completely ordinary,
但是鱼子酱和伏特加
but the caviar and the vodka
才更丰富奢华
are sublime and plentiful.
那
So.
细细品尝
Savor it.
别一次都吃光
And don't eat it all at once,
那样的话 就没有什么可享受的了
because that way, there's nothing left to enjoy.
现在 小咽一口伏特加
And now, take a little swallow of vodka
趁着嘴里还有鱼子酱
while it's still in your mouth.
你没和多少女人交往过 对吧
You haven't been with many women, have you?
星期天没有过
Not on Sundays.
你也没吃过鱼子酱 是吧
And you've never had caviar before, have you?
没吃过 女士
No, ma'am.
19岁的时候
When I was 19,
我想成为第一个
I attempted to become the first woman
横渡英吉利海峡的女人
ever to swim the English Channel.
是吗
Really?
但那天的水流很急
But the current that day was so strong that,
我每划一次 就会被推后两下
for every stroke I took, I was pushed back two.
我在水里待了32小时
I was in the water for 32 hours.
当我离加来还有2英里时
And when I was two miles from Calais,
开始下雨了
it started to rain.
就是这样 稳住
That's it! Steady on!
我实在游不动的时候
When I couldn't go any further,
我停下了
I stopped.
我就这么停下了
I just stopped.
所有人都问我 要再试试吗
And everybody asked me, would I try again?
为什么不呢
For why wouldn't I?
但我却没有尝试
But I never did.
事实上
As a matter of fact,
在那之后 我没做过什么
I've never done anything with my life after that.
你的手好粗糙
Your hands are so coarse.
我能感觉到吹向你脸颊的风
I can feel the wind in your cheek.
已经午夜了
I'm afraid it's the Witching hour.
那是第一次有女人吻我
It was the first time a woman had ever kissed me.
那是你永远不会忘记的
It's something you never forget.
你让我觉得我年轻了
I think you make me feel younger.
你也让我觉得自己年轻了
You make me feel years younger, too.
真希望我还年轻
I wish I was.
我会改变很多事
So many things I'd change.
我会弥补所有的错误
I'd undo all my mistakes.
什么错误
What mistakes?
我一直在等待
I kept waiting, you know?
想着做些什么改变现状
Thinking that I'd do something to change my circumstances.
做些什么
Do something.
逝者如斯 一去不返
Such an awful waste. You never get it back.
虚度了光阴
Wasted time.
如果我们在一起了
If we're going to have an affair,
白天不要看我
you're never to look at me during the day.
天亮前我们要分开
And we're always to part before sunrise.
不能说"我爱你"
And we will never say "I love you."
这是规定
Those are the rules.
- 你冷吗  - 冻死了
- Are you cold? - I'm freezing.
你都冻僵了
Oh, you! You're frozen.
我真笨 我穿着皮衣站在这里
What an idiot, I'm standing here in this fur.
我考虑得太不周到了
How thoughtless of me.
她是第一个爱过我的女人
She was the first woman that ever loved me.
你想让我跳过一些吗
You want me to skip some?
不用 我很高兴有人能温暖他
No, I'm glad he had somebody to keep him warm.
"我等不及再见到她了"
"I couldn't wait to see her again."
我们每晚都见面
We saw each other every night.
开同一个房间
We always used the same room.
但每一次都是新鲜的 不同的
But each time seemed new and different.
来
Come here.
Elizabeth
Elizabeth.
晚安
Good night.
直到有一晚
Until one night.
昨天 1941年12月7日
Yesterday, December 7th, 1941,
在这个国耻日里
a date which will live in infamy...
这是一次会议 一次事关未来的政治会议
It's a meeting, a policy meeting regarding your future,
可能远不止如此
possibly beyond.
同志们 计划有变
There's been a change of plan, lads.
你们可能知道或不知道
As you may or may not know,
日本人昨天轰炸了珍珠港
the Japs bombed Pearl Harbor yesterday.
Frank D. Roosevelt要求我们各司其职
Frank D. Roosevelt's asked each of us to do our part.
美国第32任总统
切尔西号
The Chelsea's been
被美国海军征用
commissioned to serve in the United States Navy.
用来维修 打捞和救援
To repair, to salvage, and to rescue.
有谁不想打仗的 现在说出来
Anybody doesn't want to go to war, now is the time to say so.
朋友 一旦你踏上那艘船 你就是海军一员了
Once you set foot on that boat, you're in the Navy, friend.
Mike 我一直想和你谈谈
Yeah, I've been meaning to talk with you, Mike.
我妻子身体欠佳
My wife's doing poorly.
我想再见她一面
I'd like to maybe see her one more time.
你现在可以回家了 Mayes先生
You're free to make your way home any way you can, Mr. Mayes.
如果他走了 谁来做饭呢
Well, if he's leaving, who's gonna cook?
食物中毒可是海上人员死亡的主要原因之一啊
Food poisoning's one of the leading causes of death at sea.
仅次于安全设备不足
Right after inadequate safety equipment.
船长 我能做饭 我做了一辈子了
I can cook, Captain. Been doing it all my life.
我不确定 你也不喜欢战争 Benjamin
I don't know. You're a little moody for war, Benjamin.
不过管他呢
What the hell?
想打倒小日本和德国佬的人
I'll take any man wants to
我带你们一起走
kick the shite out of the Japs and the Huns.
就这么定了 打包装备 我们要参战了 先生们
That's it, pack your gear. We're going to war, gentlemen!
她留了纸条
She had left a note.
她写道 "能遇见你真好"
She wrote, "It was nice to have met you."
仅此而已
And that was it.
战争和我们想的不一样
It wasn't the war any of us expected.
我们只是拖走破损的船 其实都是些破铜烂铁
We would just tow crippled ships, scraps of metal, really.
真有战争 我们也看不到
If there was a war, we didn't see it.
派给我们的主炮手非常热爱海军
There was a man assigned to us. The Chief Gunner loved the Navy.
最重要的是 他热爱美国
But most of all, he loved America.
世界上没有其他国家
There is no other country in the world.
当你拼写美国
When you spell America...
他叫Dennis Smith 是个纯血统的切罗基人
His name was Dennis Smith, and he was a full-blooded Cherokee.
他的家族在美国居住了500多年
His family had been Americans for over 500 years.
这些和平主义者说凭良心来讲 他们不会打仗
These pacifists. They say they won't fight on conscience.
要是所有人都凭良心来讲
Now, where would be if everybody decided to act
- 那会怎么样  - 小点声 好吗 长官
- according to their conscience? - Keep it down, would you, Chief?
嘿 我一直在观察你
Hey. I've been watching you.
你看起来挺可信
You seem trustworthy.
如果天有不测
If something happens to me,
你能帮我把这个给我老婆吗
could you see that this gets to my wife?
他把他的工钱都给了我 他一分钱都没花
He'd given me all of his pay. Hadn't spent a dime of it.
我想让家人知道 我惦记着他们
I want my family to know I was thinking about them.
所有人到甲板上
All hands on deck!
快滚上来 你们这些懒货
Get your asses up here, you lazy bastards!
战争最终还是来了
The war had finally found us.
停下来
All stop!
Pleasant 转一下那个灯
Pleasant, man that light.
一艘载有1300人的运输舰被鱼雷击沉了
A transport carrying 1,300 men had been split by a torpedo.
我们是第一个到达现场的
We were first to arrive at the scene.
- 关掉引擎  - 停下来
- Cut the engines! - All stop!
大海上只有我们的声音
We were the only sound.
伙计们
Fellas!
潜水艇
Sub!
我们绝对跑不过这群人
We sure as hell can't outrun them fuckers.
各就各位
Battle stations!
谢谢 长官
Thank you, Chief.
怎么了
What?
这是最后一个吗
Is that the last one?
船长
Captain!
他妈的把我的纹身打烂了
They shot the hell out of my painting!
让我握着你的手
Give me your other hand.
你会没事的 船长
You'll be all right, Captain.
他们在天堂给你留了个好位置呢
They got a nice spot in Heaven waiting for you. Nice spot.
对于生活的现状 你可以像疯狗一样不满
You can be as mad as a mad dog at the way things went.
你可以破口大骂 可以诅咒命运
You could swear, curse the Fates.
但到了生命尽头
But when it comes to the end,
你还是得放手
you have to let go.
船长
Captain?
那天 1328个人失去了生命
Thirteen hundred and twenty eight men died that day.
我跟切罗基人Dennis Smith道了永别
I said my goodbyes to the Cherokee, Dennis Smith.
还有John Grimm 他说得没错 他将葬身大海
John Grimm, who was right, he was gonna die there.
我把Pleasant Curtis的钱寄给了他的妻子
I sent Pleasant Curtis' wife his money.
我向双胞胎的Vic Brody道了别
I said goodbye to the twin, Vic Brody,
还有Mike Clark 切尔西号的船长
and to Mike Clark, captain of the tugboat Chelsea.
我和那些怀揣着梦想的人道了别
I said goodbye to all the other men who had dreams of their own,
他们有人想做保险推销员
all the men who wanted to be insurance salesmen
有人想做医生 律师 还有印第安酋长
or doctors or lawyers or Indian chiefs.
这个修不好了
This don't get fixed.
在那里 死亡不再是自然而然的了
Out here, death didn't seem natural.
我从没在这么远的海上见过蜂鸟
I'd never seen a hummingbird that far out to sea.
之前没有 之后也没有了
Before or since.
1945年5月 那年我26岁
And in May of 1945, when I was 26 years old,
我回到了家
I came home.
我准备好了 好了
I'm ready! I'm ready!
我来了
I'm coming!
- 我好了  - 好了 我来了 Alfalina小姐
- I'm ready! - All right, I'm coming, Miss Alfalina.
- Queenie  - 怎么了
- Queenie? - Yes?
我的天啊 你回家了 你居然回来了
Sweet Jesus! Oh, you're home! Oh, Lord, you came back!
- 让我好好看看你  - 妈妈 那是谁啊
- Let me look at you. - Who's that, Mama?
孩子 这是你哥哥 Benjamin
Child, it's your brother, Benjamin.
我都不知道我还有哥哥
I didn't know he was my brother.
孩子 你不知道的事情太多了
There's a shitload of things you don't know, child.
赶紧去把地扫完
Get on out there and finish sweeping.
再过来洗手 帮我摆餐桌 快去
Come here, wash your hands, help me with the table. Go on, now.
转过来 你看起来跟重生了一样
Turn around. You look like you've been born again.
比春天还有活力
Younger than the springtime.
牧师施法的时候 肯定给了你第二条生命
I think that preacher laid hands on you gave you a second life.
我看见你的时候就知道 你与众不同
I knew it that moment I saw you, you were special.
跟你说 我膝盖老疼
I tell you what, my knees are sore,
因为我每晚都跪着祈祷上帝
'cause I've been on them every night asking the Lord,
我说 "上帝啊 我只求他平安回家"
I said, "God, just bring him home safely."
记得我跟你说的吗
Remember what I told you?
"世事难料"
"You never know what's coming for you?"
没错 快坐下
That's right. Sit down.
有什么有意思的事情说来听听
Well, you learn anything worth repeating?
- 我的确经历了不少  - 你尝过了苦头
- I sure saw some things. - Oh, you seen some pain.
- 不过也有甜头  - 没错 是的
- Some joy, too? - Sure. Sure, I did.
我就是想听你说这些 看看你啊
Yeah, that's what I want to hear. Look at you.
- Tizzy呢  - 哦 孩子
- Where's Tizzy? - Oh, baby.
Weathers先生去年四月在睡梦中走了
Mr. Weathers died in his sleep one night last April.
- 妈妈 真遗憾  - 孩子 不用担心
- Mama, I'm so sorry. - Don't you worry about that, baby.
现在活着的 也就一两个了
Yeah, well, it's only one or two of them left now.
不过都还挺快活
They all just about new.
他们应该跟别人一样 都等着那一天吧
Guess they're waiting their turn like everybody else, huh?
你能回来我真是太高兴了
I'm so glad you're back home with me!
现在 我们得给你
Now, we're gonna have to
找个妻子和一份新工作 就这么定了
find you a wife and a new job! That's right.
快过来 帮我摆桌子
Come on in here, help me with this table.
Benjamin
Benjamin.
孩子 你这是在浪费时间 她聋透了
You're wasting your time, baby. She's stone deaf.
你住在DeSeroux太太以前住的房间
Oh, and you'll be staying in what was Mrs. DeSeroux's old room.
你长大了 不能和别人挤一间了
You're too big to be rooming with anybody else.
回家的感觉很奇妙
It's a funny thing about coming home.
样子没变 气味没变 感觉没变
Looks the same, smells the same, feels the same.
我有没有告诉过你 我曾被闪电击中了7次
Did I ever tell you I've been struck by lightning seven times?
一次是我开着我的车
Once when I was sitting in my truck,
心里想着自己的事
just minding my own business.
你才意识到 只有你自己变了
You realize what's changed is you.
我回来不久后的一个早晨
And late one morning, not long after I'd been back...
谢谢
Thank you.
嘿
Hey.
- 不好意思 请问Queenie在吗  - Daisy
- Excuse me, is Queenie here? - Daisy?
- 是我 Benjamin啊  - Benjamin
- It's me, Benjamin. - Benjamin?
我的天啊
Oh, my God!
当然是你 Benjamin
Of course it's you! Benjamin!
最近好吗 好久没见了
How are you? It's been such a long time.
我想知道的太多了 你什么时候回来的
There's so much I want to know. When did you get back?
几周前回来的
Well, I got back a few weeks ago.
我问Queenie了
I spoke to Queenie,
她说你在打仗 在海上的什么地方
she said you were in the war, somewhere at sea.
- 我们特别 特别担心你  - 我没事
- We were so, so worried about you. - Oh, I'm okay.
看看你啊 你真好看
Well, look at you. You're so lovely.
你后来就没给我写信了
You stopped writing.
"我离开的时候 她还是个小女孩
"When I had left, she was a girl.
现如今 已经成为了窈窕淑女
And a woman had taken her place.
她是我见过的最美的女人"
She was the most beautiful woman I'd ever seen."
美
Beautiful.
"最美"
"The most beautiful."
- 你还记得Fuller奶奶吗  - 记得啊 怎么了
- You remember Grandma Fuller? - Why, sure I do.
- 她去世了  - 我听说了 节哀吧
- She passed. - I heard that. I'm sorry.
不敢相信我们在这里见面了 真是缘分
I just can't believe we're both here. Must be fate.
不对 他们把这个叫做什么
No, no, what do they call it?
命运
Kismet.
你知道Edgar Cayce吗 那个灵媒
Do you know about Edgar Cayce, the psychic?
我觉得我不
I don't believe I...
他说万事已经命中注定
He says that everything is predetermined,
但我更觉得这是缘分
but I like to think of it as fate.
我不知道缘分是怎么回事 但我很高兴这一切发生了
I'm not sure how it works, but I'm glad it happened.
你去过曼哈顿吗 在我住处的河对岸
Have you been to Manhattan? It's right across the river from me.
如果我站在床上
Now, I can see the Empire State Building
就可以看见帝国大厦
if I stand on my bed.
你呢 你去了哪些地方
What about you? Where have you been?
全都说来我听听 上次你写信说
Tell me everything. Last time you wrote,
你去俄罗斯了
you said you'd been to Russia.
我一直都想去俄罗斯 那里真有别人说的那么冷吗
I've always wanted to go to Russia. Is it as cold as they say?
- 冷得多呢  - 我的天
- Twice as cold. - My goodness.
我们都说你不一样 但我是真心觉得你与众不同
We always said you were different. But I think you really are.
你说你遇见了喜欢的人 有结果吗
You wrote that you met somebody. Did it work out?
还是分道扬镳了
It ran its course.
对了 你还记得这个吗
Hey, do you remember this?
"这是一只老袋鼠下午5点的样子"
"This is the picture of Old Man Kangaroo at 5 in the afternoon."
一起吃个晚饭吧
Would you like to have dinner?
我有没有告诉过你 我跟着Balanchine跳舞啊
Did I tell you that I danced for Balanchine?
美国舞蹈家 编导
他是个著名的编舞家 他说我的曲线很完美
Oh, he's a famous choreographer. He said that I had perfect line.
有一次排练 有人摔倒了
You know, in a rehearsal once, a dancer fell.
然后他就 把这个动作编进舞蹈里了
And he just... He just put it right into the production.
你能想象吗 在一段经典芭蕾舞里
I mean, can you imagine that? Like in a... In a classical ballet?
让舞者故意摔倒
You know, a dancer, intentionally falling.
如今有个全新的词来形容舞蹈了 叫"抽象"
There's a whole new word for dance now. It's called "Abstract."
不过 不止他一个人这么做了
No, he's not the only one, though.
还有Lincoln Kirstein和Lucia Chase 对了
There's Lincoln Kirstein and Lucia Chase, and oh, my...
还有Agnes de Mille
Oh, there's Agnes de Mille.
她打破了常规
She's just torn up all those conventions,
就是挺胸抬头那一套
you know, all that straight-up-and-down stuff.
舞蹈不是循规蹈矩
It's not about the formality of the dance,
而是舞者的感觉
it's about what the dancer's feeling.
她跟我说的这个全新的世界
As she told me about this big new world,
那些我从未听过的名字
names that didn't mean a thing to me,
她说的话 我没听进去多少
I didn't really hear very much of what she was saying.
一切是全新的 现代的 美式的
It's new and it's modern and it's American.
他们了解我们的活力和形体
They understand our vigor and our physicality.
天 我一直在说一直在说
Oh, my God. I've just been talking and talking.
没有 我喜欢听你说 我不知道你还抽烟
No, no, I've enjoyed listening. I didn't know you smoked.
我已经长大了
I'm old enough.
我大到还可以做很多别的
I'm old enough for a lot of things.
在纽约 我们整晚不睡
In New York, we stay up all night,
看着太阳爬上仓库屋顶
watch the sun come up over the warehouses.
我们总能找些事情做
There's always something to do.
我明天就要回去了
I have to go back tomorrow.
- 这么快  - 我也想留下来
- So soon. - Wish I could stay.
舞者已经不需要服装和布景了
Dancers don't need costumes or scenery anymore.
我都能想到自己裸身跳舞的样子
I can imagine dancing completely naked.
你看过D.H.Lawrence的书吗
Have you read D. H. Lawrence?
英国作家 作品过多描写色情
- 呃  - 他的书被禁了
- Well... - His books were banned.
读他的书就像在做爱
The words are like making love.
在舞团里 大家必须相互信任
In our company, we have to trust each other.
性也是其中的一部分
Sex is a part of it.
很多舞者都是女同性恋
You know, a lot of the dancers are lesbians.
有一个女人想和我睡
There was one woman who wanted to sleep with me.
- 你会不高兴吗  - 关于哪个部分
- Does that upset you? - Which part?
有人想跟我睡
Somebody wanting to sleep with me.
你很吸引人
You're a desirable woman.
我想 大多数人都想和你睡吧
I would think most of them would want to sleep with you.
我们回去吧
Let's go back to the house.
或者开个房
Or we could get a room somewhere.
- 我可以脱下你的夹克  - 这样不好吧 Daisy
- We could lay down your jacket. - I don't know, Daisy.
不是我不想还是怎么的
It's not that I wouldn't like to or anything.
我害怕我会让你失望
I think I'll just disappoint you.
Benjamin 我和更老的人都在一起过
Oh, Benjamin, I've been with older men.
你明早就回纽约了
You're going back to New York in the morning.
你应该和你朋友在一起
You should be with your friends.
- 你只能年轻一次  - 我已经够大了
- You're only young once. - Oh, I'm old enough.
Daisy 今晚不行
Daisy, just not tonight, is all.
我们可以去听听音乐
We could go hear some music.
我们的生命因机遇而有意义
Our lives are defined by opportunities.
甚至包括我们错过的
Even the ones we miss.
你英俊潇洒 风度翩翩
You look so handsome and so distinguished.
他们说飓风不会来了 刚好从这儿刮走
They're saying the hurricane's gonna miss us, blow right on by.
- 那太好了  - 我要和妈妈一起在毯子下面躺着
- Oh, that's great. - I'll stay under the blankets with Mother.
她什么也没说 Benjamin
She says nothing... Benjamin?
"我的生活 又发生了不一样的"
"Things were becoming different..."
变化
...for me.
我的白发褪去 黑发像野草一样生长
My hair had very little gray and grew like weeds.
我的嗅觉更灵敏 听力也更敏锐
My sense of smell was keener. My hearing, more acute.
我能走得更快更远
I could walk further and faster.
当所有人都在老去 我却独自返老还童
While everybody else was aging, I was getting younger, all alone.
进来吧
Come in.
Benjamin
Benjamin.
- 还记得我吗  - 当然了 Button先生
- Do you remember me? - Well, sure I do, Mr. Button.
- 你怎么了  - 脚感染了 那个
- What happened to you? - Darn foot. Got infected, so...
欢迎回家 朋友
Welcome home, my friend.
你还是喜欢把萨泽拉克和威士忌混起来喝啊
I see you're still drinking your Sazerac with whiskey.
习惯了
Creature of habit.
你还去波旁大道那边的房子吗
You still visiting the house on Bourbon Street?
很久没去了
Not for a long time.
说来有意思
Interesting times, though.
我们从每天做4万个纽扣
We went from making 40,000
到现在一天做50万
to nearly half a million buttons a day.
雇佣的员工是以前的10倍
We employed 10 times the number of people.
我们日以继夜地赶工
We were operating around the clock.
说来惭愧
Damn shame.
战争让纽扣生意更好了
The war has been kind to the button industry.
知道吗
You know,
我病了 不知道还能活多久
I'm sick. I don't know how much longer I have.
- 我很抱歉 Button先生  - 不用这么说
- I'm sorry to hear that, Mr. Button. - No...
我没什么朋友 习惯独来独往
I don't have any people. I keep to myself.
希望你不要介意 但是如果可能的话
I hope you don't mind, but, whenever possible,
我希望你能陪着我
I'd enjoy your company.
我会尽力而为的
I'll certainly do what I can.
Benjamin 你了解纽扣生意吗
Benjamin, do you know anything about buttons?
现在 Button纽扣生意已经在家族中传承了124年了
Now, Button's Buttons has been in our family for 124 years.
我爷爷是位裁缝 在里士满开了间小铺子
My grandfather was a tailor, and he had a small shop in Richmond.
内战之后 他搬去了新奥尔良
After the Civil War, he moved to New Orleans,
在那里 我爸爸凭借聪明才智 开始经营纽扣生意
where my father had the wisdom to make our own buttons.
在他的经营下 裁缝铺扩张到了现在的规模
So, with his help, the tailor shop grew to this.
而现在 我连线都不会缝
And today, I can't sew a stitch.
这故事很有意思
That's very, very interesting.
您自己做得也很好啊
You sure have done well for yourself.
那我能帮你什么呢 Button先生
So, what can I do for you, Mr. Button?
Benjamin 你是我的儿子
Benjamin? You're my son.
很抱歉 我之前没有告诉你
I'm so sorry I never told you before.
你出生在大战结束的那一晚
You were born the night the Great War ended.
你妈妈难产而死
Your mother died giving birth to you.
我以为你是个怪物
I thought you were a monster.
我向你妈妈保证过 会让你平安
I promised your mother I'd make sure you were safe.
我不该抛弃你
I should never have abandoned you.
我妈妈
My mother?
在庞恰特雷恩湖边的避暑别墅
At the summer house on Lake Pontchartrain.
我小的时候 喜欢比别人起得都早
When I was a boy, I'd love to wake up before anyone else,
跑到湖边 迎接新一天的到来
run down to that lake and watch the day begin.
那时 我觉得自己是世界上唯一的生命
It was as if I was the only one alive.
我对她一见钟情
I fell in love the first time I saw her.
你妈妈叫Caroline Murphy
Your mother's name was Caroline Murphy.
她在你爷爷的厨房里工作
She worked in your grandfather's kitchen.
她来自都柏林
She's from Dublin.
1903年 Caroline和
In 1903, Caroline and all
她所有兄弟姐妹
her brothers and sisters came to live here,
来新奥尔良生活
in New Orleans.
我总会找理由下到厨房
I'd find excuses to go down to that kitchen
这样就能看到她
just so I could look at her.
1918年4月25日 是我人生中最幸福的一天
April 25th, 1918. Happiest day of my life.
那天 我娶了你的妈妈
The day I married your mother.
你为什么不早告诉我呢
Why didn't you just tell me?
我打算把我所有财产都留给你
I plan on leaving everything I have to you.
- 我要走了  - 去哪儿
- I have to go. - Where?
回家
Home.
他到底怎么想的
And what does he think, anyway?
他觉得自己这么冒出来
He thinks he can just show up
然后所有事情就柳暗花明了
and everything's supposed to be fine and dandy.
然后大家就能和和气气了
Everybody's just supposed to be friends.
这事儿他肯定不能如意
Well, he got another thing coming, that's for sure.
老天有眼 这事儿他绝对不能如意
God be my witness, he got another thing coming.
我找到你的那晚 他只留了18美元
He left us $18 that night you was found.
18张烂票子
Eighteen ratty dollars
- 还有块脏兮兮的尿布  - 晚安 妈妈
- and a filthy diaper. - Good night, Mama.
晚安 孩子
Good night, baby.
我有没有告诉过你 我曾被闪电击中了7次
Did I ever tell you I was struck by lightning seven times?
有一次 我在路上遛狗
Once, I was walking my dog down the road.
现在我一只眼瞎了 听力也衰退了
I'm blind in the one eye, can't hardly hear,
莫名其妙地抽搐 发抖
get twitches and shakes out of nowhere,
也总是记不住东西
always losing my line of thought.
但你知道吗
But you know what?
上帝一直在提醒我 活着就很幸运了
God keeps reminding me I'm lucky to be alive.
暴风雨要来了
Storm's coming.
先生 需要帮助吗 上楼第一间卧室
May I help you, sir? Up the stairs, first bedroom.
谢谢
Thank you.
醒醒
Wake up.
我帮你穿上衣服
Let's get you dressed.
真是麻烦了
Now that's something.
谢谢
Thank you.
对于生活的现状 你可以像疯狗一样不满
You can be mad as a mad dog at the way things went.
你可以破口大骂 可以诅咒命运
You can swear and curse the Fates.
但到了生命尽头
But when it comes to the end,
你还是得放手
you have to let go.
这葬礼很体面
Well, it sure is a beautiful service.
他会被葬在你妈妈的旁边
He'll be buried right next to your mother.
你才是我妈妈
You're my mother.
我的孩子
My baby-
我从没来过纽约
Now, I'd never seen New York.
- 不好意思 我是Daisy的朋友  - 这边请
- Excuse me, I'm a friend of Daisy's. - Right this way.
- Daisy有人找 Daisy  - 来了
- Daisy has company. Daisy! Daisy! - Yes!
- 我们需要服装  - 谁找我
- We need the wardrobe. -ls somebody looking for me?
- Benjamin  - 嗨
- Benjamin. - Hi.
- 你来这里干什么  - 想着来看看
- What are you doing here? - Thought I'd come visit.
要是可以 想陪陪你
Spend some time with you, if I could.
你提前打个电话就好了 你让我措手不及
Oh, well, I wish you would've called. You took me by surprise.
- 你可以把花扔了  - 不会的 很好看 谢谢
- You can just throw them out. - No. Thank you, they're lovely.
我刚一直在看你
I couldn't take my eyes off of you.
你太让我着迷了
I thought you were mesmerizing.
谢谢你这么说
Thank you. That's very kind of you to say.
我先去换衣服了 等会儿我们要去派对
I better get changed. A group of us are going to a party.
- 你想来吗  - 我听说有家餐厅不错
- Would you want to come? - Someone told me about a restaurant
我觉得你可能会喜欢
I thought you might enjoy.
以防万一 我还订座了
I made a reservation, just in case.
所有的舞者演出后都会去聚聚
Just, all the dancers go out after the show. You're...
你跟我们一起来吧 我去换衣服 好吗
You're welcome to come with us. I'll get changed. All right?
她还给俄罗斯芭蕾舞团排过舞
She choreographs for the Ballets Russes.
她太厉害了
She's divine.
你真美
You were breathtaking.
亲爱的
Sweetie.
这是David 他也是舞团的
This is David. He dances with the company.
- 这是Benjamin  - 谁
- This is Benjamin. - Who?
- 我跟你说过的  - 哦对 你好吗
- I told you about him. - Oh, yeah. How you doing?
- 我去给你拿杯喝的  - 好 谢谢
- I'll go get you a drink. - All right. Thanks.
你是她奶奶的朋友
So, you were a friend of her grandmother's?
还是什么
Or something like that?
差不多吧
Something like that.
失陪了
Hey, excuse me.
过来吧
Come on.
嘿
Hey!
我真不知道你会来
Now, I had no idea you were coming.
天啊 Benjamin
Lord, Benjamin.
你想让我怎么样呢 想让我放下这一切吗
What did you expect? What, you want me to drop everything?
这是我的生活
Now, this is my life.
亲爱的 去市区吗
Babe! You going downtown?
来吧 你会玩得很开心的
Come on. You'll have a good time.
那里有很多音乐家和有趣的人
There's lots of musicians, interestig people.
不用了 这都是我的错
You don't have to do that. This is my fault.
我应该提前打电话的
I should've called.
我想着我过来
I thought I'd come here
能给你一个惊喜呢
and sweep you off your feet or something.
- Daisy 快来 走了  - 马上来
- Daisy! Come on! Let's go. - Be right there.
他人不错
Seems nice.
你爱他吗
Do you love him?
爱吧
I think so.
我为你高兴
I'm happy for you.
那回家见吧
Maybe I'll see you at home.
好
Okay.
我很喜欢你的演出
I enjoyed the show!
他来是想告诉我 他父亲死了
He came to tell me his father had died.
- 你也预料不到的  - 我那时才23  什么都不在乎
- You couldn't have known. - I was 23. I... I just didn't care.
然后你做了什么
What did you do next?
有些照片 我记得在包的前袋里
Some photographs, I think, in the front of my bag.
我那时是个挺不错的舞者
I was as good a dancer as I was ever gonna be.
有那么5年 我
For five years, I...
我在世界各地表演
I danced everywhere.
伦敦 维也纳 布拉格
London, Vienna, Prague.
我从没见过这些照片
I've never seen these.
妈
Mom.
你从没说过你的舞蹈生涯
You never talked about your dancing.
我是唯一一个受邀
Well, I was the only American
和莫斯科大剧院芭蕾舞团共舞的美国人 宝贝
to be invited to dance with the Bolshoi, sugar.
真是太棒了
It was glorious.
但我从没忘记Benjamin
But Benjamin was never far from my thoughts.
我会不自觉地说
And I'd find myself saying...
晚安 Benjamin
Good night, Benjamin.
- "晚安 Daisy"   - 他也这么说
- "Good night, Daisy." - He said that?
"生活并不是那么错综复杂
"Life wasn't all that complicated.
要是愿意 你也可以说我是在寻找"
If you want, you might say I was looking for something."
Benjamin La Tourneau太太去世了
Benjamin? Mrs. La Tourneau just passed.
- 有Benjamin Button先生的信  - 我就是
- Letter for Mr. Benjamin Button? - That'd be me.
谢谢
Thank you.
我找Daisy Fuller小姐
Miss Daisy Fuller.
- 稍等 请坐一会儿  - 好的
- Just a minute. Please have a seat. - Sure.
有时候 我们的人生会与别人的碰撞
Sometimes we're on a collision course
只是我们不知道而已
and we just don't know it.
无论是意外 还是注定
Whether it's by accident or by design,
我们都无法改变
there's not a thing we can do about it.
一位在巴黎的女子要出门购物
A woman in Paris was on her way to go shopping.
她忘了带外套 于是就回去拿
But she had forgotten her coat, went back to get it.
她拿上了外套 电话响了
When she had gotten her coat, the phone had rung.
然后她接起电话 聊了一会儿
So she had stopped to answer it and talked for a couple of minutes.
这个女子打电话时
While the woman was on the phone,
Daisy正在为巴黎歌剧院的演出做彩排
Daisy was rehearsing for a performance at the Paris Opera House.
彩排时 这个女子挂了电话
And while she was rehearsing, the woman, off the phone now,
出门打出租车
had gone outside to get a taxi.
出租车司机送完了上一位客人
Now, a taxi driver had dropped off a fare earlier,
停车去买咖啡
and had stopped to get a cup of coffee.
与此同时 Daisy还在排练
And all the while, Daisy was rehearsing.
那位刚送完了客人
And this cab driver, who dropped off the earlier fare
停车去买咖啡的司机
and had stopped to get the cup of coffee,
恰好接到了要去购物的女子
he picked up the lady who was going shopping
正因如此 那位女子错过了上一辆出租车
and had missed getting the earlier cab.
有个男人过马路 车子只好停下
The taxi had to stop for a man crossing the street,
这个男人比平时晚起了5分钟
who had left for work five minutes later than he normally did
因为他忘了上闹钟
because he forgot to set his alarm.
当那个工作迟到的人横穿马路的时候
While that man, late for work, was crossing the street,
Daisy已经彩排结束 正在洗澡
Daisy had finished rehearsing and was taking a shower.
Daisy洗澡的时候
And while Daisy was showering,
出租车停在店门口
the taxi was waiting outside a boutique
等那位女子取包裹
for the woman to pick up a package
而包裹还没打包好
which hadn't been wrapped yet,
因为打包的女孩
because the girl who was supposed to wrap it
前一晚和她男朋友分手 然后就忘了
had broken up with her boyfriend the night before and forgot.
打包好之后 女子回到出租车上
When the package was wrapped, the woman, who was back in the cab,
又被一辆货车挡住去路
was blocked by a delivery truck.
这时候 Daisy正在穿衣服
All the while, Daisy was getting dressed.
货车开走了 出租车重新上路
The delivery truck pulled away, and the taxi was able to move
Daisy最后一个穿好衣服
while Daisy, the last to be dressed,
又等了一会儿她断了鞋带的朋友
waited for one of her friends who had broken a shoelace.
出租车停下等红绿灯时
While the taxi was stopped, waiting for a traffic light,
Daisy和她朋友从剧院后门出来
Daisy and her friend came out the back of the theater.
如果有一件事不一样
And if only one thing had happened differently,
如果鞋带没有断
if that shoelace hadn't broken
如果那货车早一点开走
or that delivery truck had moved moments earlier
或者包裹早已打包好
or that package had been wrapped and ready
因为女孩没跟她男朋友分手
because the girl hadn't broken up with her boyfriend,
或者那个男人定了闹钟 早起5分钟
or that man had set his alarm and got up five minutes earlier
或者司机没有停下来买咖啡
or that taxi driver hadn't stopped for a cup of coffee
或者那个女子记得带外套
or that woman had remembered
然后上了前一辆出租车
her coat and got into an earlier cab,
Daisy和她朋友就能安全穿过马路
Daisy and her friend would have crossed the street
那出租车也只是擦肩而过
and the taxi would have driven by.
但生活就是这样
But, life being what it is,
一系列生活的交错和意外
a series of intersecting lives and incidents
没人能够控制
out of anyone's control,
出租车没有和她们擦肩而过
that taxi did not go by,
那时司机又分了神
and that driver was momentarily distracted.
Daisy
Daisy!
出租车就撞到了Daisy
And that taxi hit Daisy.
Daisy 来人啊
Daisy! Help!
她的腿被撞断了
And her leg was crushed.
Daisy
Daisy?
- 谁告诉你的  - 你朋友给我写信了
- Who told you? - Your friend wired me.
这么远来看我 你真是太好了
Very kind of you to come all this way to see that I was all right.
要是你 你也会这么做的
You'd do the same for me.
天哪
My God.
看看你 多完美啊
Look at you. You're perfect.
我真希望你没来
I wish you hadn't come here.
我不想让你看到我这副样子
I don't want you to see me like this.
她的腿5处断裂
Her leg had been broken in five places.
如果进行长时间治疗 她或许能重新走路
And with therapy and time, she might walk again.
但是再也不能跳舞了
But she'd never dance.
我要带你回家
I'm gonna take you home with me.
- 我想照顾你  - 我不回新奥尔良
- I want to look after you. - I'm not going back to New Orleans.
那我就留在巴黎
Then I'll stay here in Paris.
你听不懂吗 我不想让你帮我
Don't you understand? I don't want your help.
我现在是很难过
I know I'm feeling sorry for myself,
但我也不想跟你在一起
but I don't want to be with you.
在纽约我就告诉你了 你就是不听
Tried to tell you that in New York. You don't listen.
你可能会改变主意
You might change your mind.
我们都不是小孩儿了 Benjamin
We are not little children anymore, Benjamin.
别再掺和我的生活了
Just stay out of my life.
我太狠心了
I was awfully cruel.
他不明白 我只是不想让他看到我那副样子
He didn't understand. I couldn't have him see me like that.
"我并没有马上离开
"I didn't leave right away.
我在巴黎待了一段时间 暗中照顾她"
I stayed in Paris for a while to look out for her."
我都不知道呢
I never knew that.
亲爱的 能帮我叫下护士吗
Oh, darling, could you get the nurse?
我重新学会走路
I taught myself to walk again.
我坐了火车去卢尔德
I took the train to Lourdes.
我看看 很正常 脉搏缓下来了
Let's take a look. That's normal. Pulse rate is slowing.
稍后可能会呼吸困难
She is gonna struggle to breathe.
- 你没事吧  - 没事
- Will you be all right? - Yeah.
好了 他写道 "我回到家"
All right, he says, "I went back home."
这里有很多页被撕掉了
And then there's a lot of pages torn out.
"我听着房子里的声音" 我读过了
"I listened to the sound of the house." I read that already.
他
He...
他把什么洒到纸上了 看不清
He spilt something on it, so it's hard to read, Mom.
好像是关于航海的 你知道是什么吗
Something about sailing, does that make sense?
我用父亲留在湖边别墅的帆船学会了航行
I learned to sail an old boat of my father's from the lake house.
说实话
I can't lie.
我的确很享受有一两位姑娘的陪伴
I did enjoy the company of a woman or two.
或者3位
Or maybe three.
不知道你为什么烦心
Don't know why you bother,
Sam 明天还是要去的
Sam, just gonna be there again tomorrow.
妈妈
Mama.
1962年春天
And in the spring of 1962,
她回来了
she came back.
- 你想知道我去哪里了吗  - 不想
- You want to know where I've been? - No.
你怎么也不写信呢
How come you didn't write or nothing?
莫名其妙就消失了
Just disappearing like that.
我只是处理了一下私事
It was something I needed to do for myself.
就是说嘛 我也从不觉得你是自私的人
Yeah, well, I never took you to be the selfish type.
但愿如此
I sure hope I'm not wrong.
我看人很准的
I'm usually not wrong about people.
- 晚安 妈妈  - 晚安 孩子
- Good night, Mama. - Good night, baby.
你们玩得开心
Y'all have fun.
- 你都没怎么说话  - 我不想毁了这个气氛
- You haven't said two words. - I don't want to ruin it.
- 和我睡吧  - 当然了
- Sleep with me? - Absolutely.
我邀请她跟我出游
I asked her to come away with me.
我们沿着佛罗里达群岛 一路驶进墨西哥湾
We sailed into the Gulf along the Florida Keys.
我很庆幸26岁那年我没和你在一起
I am so glad we didn't find one another when I was 26.
- 为什么这么说  - 那时我太年轻
- Why do you say that? - I was so young.
你也太老了
And you were so old.
瓜熟蒂落 水到渠成
It happened when it was supposed to happen.
我会珍惜和你在一起的每分每秒
I will enjoy each and every moment I have with you.
我打赌 我在这能比你坚持得更久
I bet I can stay out here longer than you.
你肯定不行
I bet you can't.
你脸上都没有皱纹
Barely a line or a crease.
而我每天都会多长几条 不公平
Every day I have more wrinkles. It's not fair.
我爱你的皱纹 所有皱纹都爱
I love your wrinkles. Both of them.
越来越年轻是什么感觉
What's it like growing younger?
真是不好说 我看不到所有变化
I can't really say. I'm always looking out my own eyes.
当我的皮肤下垂变老了 你还爱我吗
Will you still love me when my skin grows old and saggy?
当我的脸上长满青春痘 还尿床 你还爱我吗
Will you still love me when I have acne? When I wet the bed?
当我害怕楼梯下的东西时 你还爱我吗
When I'm afraid of what's under the stairs?
怎么了
What?
你在想什么
What are you thinking?
我在想 为什么没有永恒呢
Well, I was thinking how nothing lasts.
多遗憾啊
And what a shame that is.
有些事情是永垂不朽的
Some things last.
- 晚安 Daisy  - 晚安 Benjamin
- Good night, Daisy. - Good night, Benjamin.
妈
Mom?
- 你什么时候遇见爸爸的  - 在那之后
- When did you meet Dad? - Some time after that.
你跟他说过Benjamin的事吗
Did you tell him about this Benjamin?
他知道得够多了 亲爱的
He knew enough, darling.
妈妈
Mama?
Queenie
Queenie?
有事吗
Hello?
嗨 Carter太太 我是Benjamin 大家都去哪儿了
Oh, hi, Mrs. Carter, it's Benjamin. Where is everybody?
Benjamin Queenie去世了 我很抱歉
Oh, Benjamin. Queenie died. I'm so sorry.
节哀顺变吧 她是个了不起的人
I'm so sorry for your loss. She was a great woman.
我们深表哀悼
Our deepest condolences.
我们把她葬在她的挚爱 Weathers先生身边
We buried her beside her beloved Mr. Weathers.
为了过上我们自己的生活
And so we might have memories of our own,
我们卖掉了我父亲的房子
we sold my father's house on Esplanade.
亲爱的 这房子真是太棒了
It is a wonderful old place, darling.
我们在这里会很幸福的
I think we are going to be so happy here.
家族历史好久远啊
Oh, what a long family history you have.
和这座房子一样久远
They come with the house.
- 来吧  - 你一定得看看主卧
- Come on. - You have to see the master suite.
我们买了一套复式公寓
We bought ourselves a duplex.
我特爱那套房子
I loved that house.
那里有柴火的味道
It smelled like firewood.
别停 继续 亲爱的
Don't... Don't stop, darling.
"那是我生命中最快乐的时光"
"It was one of the happiest times of my life."
我们连像样的家具都没有
We didn't have a stick of furniture.
我们在起居室野餐
We would have picnics in the living room.
想吃饭的时候才吃 只要想 就可以整夜不睡
We ate when we felt like it. Stayed up all night when we wanted.
我们发誓 不过循规蹈矩的生活
We vowed never to fall into routine,
不按时睡觉 不按时起床
to go to bed or wake up at the same time.
我们就在床垫上生活
We lived on that mattress.
我们的邻居 Van Dam太太 是个理疗师
Our neighbor, a Mrs. Van Dam, was a physical therapist.
我们住的地方离公共泳池有四个街区
We lived four blocks from a public pool.
你也许 还能多跳几年舞
You know, you might've got a few more years out of it,
但你选择的事业太独一无二
but you chose to do something so special and unique
只有短短几年黄金时期
that there was only a short window of time you could do it.
所以 即使没有发生意外
So, even if nothing ever happened,
你还是会回到现在的地方
you'd still be right here where you are now.
我就是不喜欢变老
I just don't like getting old.
他们在泳池里放了太多漂白粉了
They put too much chlorine in here.
我发誓 我再也不会自怨自艾了
I promise you I'll never lose myself to self-pity again.
就在那时
And I think right there and then
她明白了 没有人能够永远完美
she realized none of us is perfect forever.
她回归了平静
She found peace.
她开了间舞蹈室 教小女孩跳舞
She opened a studio and taught young girls how to dance.
足尖点地
And tendu...
从另一条路回来 点地 点地 点地 好极了
Come back the other way. And spot, spot, spot. Excellent.
- 晚安 Daisy老师  - 晚安
- Good night, Miss Daisy. - Good night.
你看起来很美
You certainly are beautiful to watch.
跳舞最重要的就是身线
Dancing's all about the line.
身体的曲线
The line of your body.
你迟早会身材走形 然后再无挽回的余地
Sooner or later, you lose that line, and you never get it back.
你是1918年生的 现在49岁了
I figure, you were born in 1918, 49 years ago.
我43岁
I'm 43.
我们可以算是同龄人了
We are almost the same age.
我们在人生的中点相遇
We're meeting in the middle.
我们总算追上彼此了
We finally caught up with each other.
等等
Wait.
我想记住我们现在的样子
I want to remember us just as we are now.
我怀孕了
I'm pregnant.
我发誓那护士说漏嘴了 说是男孩
You know, I swear the nurse slipped and said it was a boy.
但我觉得是女孩
But I think it's a girl.
- 我知道你很担心  - 我也没藏着
- I know you're afraid. - I'm not hiding it.
好吧
Okay.
- 你最担心什么  - 孩子像我一样出生
- What's your worst fear? - Baby born like me.
那我会更爱他的
Then I will love it all the more.
我越来越年轻
Okay. How can I be a father
怎么能当好父亲呢
when I'm heading in the other direction?
对孩子来说不公平 我也不想变成累赘
It's not fair to a child. I don't want to be anybody's burden.
宝贝 到头来我们都会用上尿布
Sugar, we all end up in diapers.
我会让一切顺利的
I am gonna make this work.
我想要这个孩子 和你一起养
I want this, and I want it with you.
你想要的我都会给你
I want you to have everything you want, all of it.
我只是没有想好怎么协调这一切
I'm just not sure how to reconcile this.
你会跟盲人说 他不能有孩子吗
Would you tell a blind man he couldn't have children?
好了
Here you go.
你是孩子的父亲 能当多久当多久
You'll be a father for as long as you can.
我知道会是什么结局 我已经接受了
I know the consequences. I've accepted that.
我可以不惜一切去爱你
Loving you is worth everything to me.
我去上个厕所
I have to go pee.
有史以来横渡英吉利海峡的最年长的妇女
The oldest woman to ever swim the English Channel
今日抵达加来
arrived here today in Calais...
- 不用找了  - 游了34小时
- Keep it. - ...having made the swim in 34 hours,
22分14秒
22 minutes and 14 seconds.
现年68岁的Elizabeth Abbott
The 68-year-old Elizabeth Abbott
于格林威治时间5点38分抵达
arrived at 5:38 Greenwich mean time,
她精疲力尽 但倍感开心
exhausted but happy.
Abbott女士 能用几句话来总结下您的成功吗
Miss Abbott, how would you sum up, in words, this achievement?
我觉得
I suppose...
一切皆有可能
Anything's possible.
- 好了吗  - 好了 谢谢
- All right? - Yes. Thank you.
- 可以走了吗  - 非常感谢
- You ready? - Thank you very much.
谢谢 谢谢大家
Thank you. Thank you all.
- 嗯  - 你们真好
- Yeah. - You're very kind.
春天 普通的一天里
In the spring, on a day like any other...
我1小时就回来
I'll be back in an hour!
亲爱的
Honey?
去叫救护车
Go and call an ambulance!
我快生了
The baby's coming.
接线员 我要救护车
Operator, I need an ambulance.
- 快生了  - 拿破仑路2714号
- The baby's coming! - 2714 Napoleon.
好了 保持呼吸
There you go. Keep breathing.
深呼吸 用力
Deep breaths. Push.
好了
There we go.
母女平安 是个健康的女孩儿
Everyone's fine. She's a perfectly healthy baby girl.
亲爱的
Honey?
她生下了一个将近4.8斤的女孩
She gave birth to a five pound, four ounce baby girl.
你数了脚趾头吗
Did you count the toes?
她好漂亮
She's perfect.
"我们用我母亲的名字给她取名为Caroline"
"And we named her for my mother, Caroline."
这个Benjamin是我爸爸
This Benjamin was my father?
你就这么告诉我真相的
And this is how you tell me?
失陪一下
Excuse me.
特大飓风所需的条件都已具备
...because all the ingredients are there for a major storm,
本次飓风可高达第5级
possibly even up to a Category 5.
我知道你很难受 但不能在这里吸烟
Hey, I know it's hard. You can't smoke in here.
飓风登陆点尚不知晓
Nobody can tell you exactly where it's gonna hit,
我们会查找已有资料
but we have to go with the guidance that we have,
整理好信息 并告知你们
incorporate that information and then pass it along to you.
"正如医生说的 你正常 健康地成长"
"You grew as the doctor had promised, normal and healthy."
你得给她找个真正的父亲
You're gonna have to find a real father for her.
你胡说什么
What are you talking about?
得有人陪着她慢慢变老
She's gonna need someone to grow old with.
她会学着接受这一切的 她爱你
She'll learn to accept whatever happens. She loves you.
亲爱的 她需要的是父亲 不是玩伴
Honey, she needs a father, not a playmate.
- 是因为我吗  - 不是
- Is it me? - Of course not.
- 是我变老了 你就觉得烦了  - 当然不是
- Is my age beginning to bother you? - Of course not.
你是不是就这个意思
Is that what you're telling me?
你没法同时养我们两个
You can't raise the both of us.
那是你的1岁生日 我们为你办了场派对
It was your first birthday. We had a party for you.
房间里都是小孩儿
The house was filled with children.
- 你好啊  - 嘿 兄弟
- How are you? - Hey, man.
一瞬间 他们就该上高中 谈恋爱了
Before you turn around, they'll be in high school, dating.
我卖掉了庞恰特雷恩湖边的避暑别墅
I sold the summer house on Lake Pontchartrain,
卖掉了Button纽扣厂
I sold Button's Buttons,
卖掉了我父亲的船 把钱都存进了银行
I sold my father's sailboat, put it all into a savings account.
这样你和你妈妈就能过上好日子了
And so that you and your mother might have a life,
在你记得我之前 我离开了你
I left, before you could ever remember me.
"我只带走了身上的衣服"
"I left with just the clothes on my back."
我不想再读了
I don't want to read this now.
你能直接告诉我他去了哪里吗
Can you just tell me where he went?
我也不知道
I don't really know.
这是给我的 1970年 我2岁 "生日快乐
It's for me. 1970. I was two. "Happy Birthday.
"我希望我能在临睡前吻你"
"I wish I could have kissed you good night."
这些都是给我的
They're all for me.
5岁 "我希望我能够
Five. "I wish I could
在你第一天上学的时候领着你去"
have taken you to your first day of school."
6岁 "我希望我可以在你身边 教你弹钢琴"
Six. "I wish I could have been there to teach you to play piano."
1981年 13岁
1981,13.
"我希望我可以告诉你 别去追那些男生"
"I wish I could have told you not to chase some boy.
"我希望你心碎的时候 有我陪着你"
"I wish I could have held you when you had a broken heart.
"我希望我可以做你的父亲
"I wish I could have been your father.
没有什么比这更重要"
Nothing I ever did will replace that."
我猜他去了印度
I guess he went to India.
"有意义的事 再晚做都不迟"
"For what it's worth, it's never too late,
- "不过我应该说 再早做"  - 不过我应该说 再早做
- "Or, in my case, too early..." - ...or, in my case, too early,
做你想做的人
to be whoever you want to be.
这事没有时间限制 可以随时开始
There's no time limit. Start whenever you want.
你可以改变 也可以一成不变
You can change or stay the same.
这事没有什么规矩
There are no rules to this thing.
我们可以活得出彩 也可以一败涂地
We can make the best or the worst of it.
但我希望你能活出精彩
And I hope you make the best of it.
我希望你能见识到让你惊叹的事
I hope you see things that startle you.
我希望你能体验你从未体验过的感觉
I hope you feel things you never felt before.
我希望你能遇见不同想法的人
I hope you meet people with a different point of view.
我希望你能过着引以为豪的生活
I hope you live a life you're proud of.
如果你发现你并不觉得自豪 我希望你有勇气
And if you find that you're not, I hope you have the strength
- 重新开始  - "重新开始"
- to start all over again. - "...start all over again."
他离开了很长时间
He had been gone a long time.
下周四再见
I'll see you next Thursday.
- 晚安 Daisy老师  - 晚安 亲爱的
- Good night, Miss Daisy. - Oh, good night, sweetheart.
不好意思 我们下班了
I'm sorry, we're closing.
我能帮你什么吗
Can I help you?
你是来接孩子的吗
Are you here to pick somebody up?
你为什么要回来
Why did you come back?
妈妈
Mom?
妈
你准备好了吗
You ready yet?
怎么了
Mom, what's wrong?
就是刚听说了一个朋友的噩耗
I was just hearing a very sad story about a mutual friend
我很久没见的朋友
who I hadn't seen for a very long time.
Caroline 这是Benjamin
Caroline, this is Benjamin.
你还是个婴儿的时候就认识他
You knew him when you were just a baby.
- 嗨  - 嗨
- Hi. - Hi.
嘿
Hey.
抱歉 我以为你准备好了
Oh, I'm sorry, I thought you were done.
哦 这位是我家的世交
Oh, this is a friend of my family's.
Benjamin Button 这是我丈夫 Robert
Benjamin Button, this is my husband, Robert.
- 你好吗  - 幸会
- How do you do? - A pleasure.
很高兴认识你
Well, it was very nice to meet you.
- 我们在车里等你 亲爱的  - 好的
- We'll be in the car, darling. - All right.
再见
Bye.
我去关门
I'm just locking up.
哇
Wow.
她真漂亮 跟她妈妈一样
She's beautiful. Like her mother.
- 她也跳舞吗  - 跳得不怎么好
- Does she dance? - Not very well.
可能是遗传我吧
I guess that'd be from my side of things.
她是个贴心的好姑娘
She's a dear, sweet girl.
只是有点迷茫 不过 谁12岁的时候不是呢
She seems a little lost. But then, who isn't at 12?
她总是让我想起你
A lot of her reminds me of you.
我丈夫 是鳏夫 呃 曾经是
My husband, he's a widower, or was... Was a widower.
他很善良 很阳光 爱冒险
He's an incredibly kind, just bright, adventurous man.
- 他也是个好父亲  - 真好
- He's been a terrific father. - Good.
- 你又年轻了好多  - 只是外表
- You are so much younger. - Only on the outside.
你说得对
You were right.
我没法同时养你们两个
I couldn't have been raising both of you.
我没那么坚强
I'm not that strong.
你住哪里
So, where are you staying?
你打算干什么
What are you gonna do?
我住在庞恰特雷恩酒店
I'm staying at the Pontchartrain Hotel on the Avenue.
我不知道该干什么
I don't know what I'm gonna do.
但是
But...
他们还在等我
They're waiting.
这我记得 那就是他吗
I remember that. That was him?
飓风改变了方向
The hurricane has changed directions.
不久后就会登陆
It's going to make landfall sometime soon.
- 我是不是该做些什么  - 正在组织
- Am I supposed to do something? - Arrangements are being made
撤离人员 不过还是看你
to move people, but it's up to you.
不了 我们留下来
No. No, we're... We're staying.
情况有变我会通知你
I'll let you know if anything changes.
"那一晚
"That night, while I was
我坐在那里思考自己为什么回来"
sitting and wondering why I came back at all,
"就有人敲门了"
"There was a knock at the door."
进来吧
Come in.
你还好吗
Are you all right?
抱歉 我不知道我来这里干什么
I'm sorry, I don't know what I'm doing here.
没有什么会永垂不朽
Nothing lasts.
我爱你 这点从未变过
I have never stopped loving you.
但是 Benjamin 我已经老了
Oh, but, Benjamin, I'm an old woman now.
有些事 你永远不会忘记
Some things you never forget.
很少有人知道
...so few people even know
你最初还进过监狱
that you were ever in jail in the first place.
告诉你吧 我也觉得不爽
I'll tell you, I am sick about it, too,
因为 就算他们不给你颁"年度人物"这样的大奖
because, please, if they're not gonna give you an award
他们至少能把你的名字
like "Man of the Year," At least what they could do
从前罪犯档案中除掉
is stop having you listed as an ex-convict
我还是觉得 这不公平
which I think is, again, so unfair.
晚安 Benjamin
Good night, Benjamin.
晚安 Daisy
Good night, Daisy.
和预想的一样 我看着她离开
And as I knew I would, I watched her go.
这是他写的最后一件事了
That's the last thing he wrote.
你父亲去世后的一天
Sometime after your father passed,
我接到一个电话
there was a call.
你好
Hello.
是的 请讲
Yes, speaking.
不好意思 我没明白
I'm sorry, I don't understand.
就在拐角那个房子停下
It's the corner house.
进来吧
Come on in.
- 我是Daisy Fuller  - 我是David Hernandez
- I'm Daisy Fuller. - I'm David Hernandez,
是儿童福利中心奥尔良分局的
with the Orleans Parish Department of Child Welfare Services.
他住在危楼里
He was living in a condemned building.
警察找到了这个
The police found this with him.
这个日记 里面还很多次提到你的名字
This address. It's got your name in it a lot.
他的健康状况不太乐观 被送去了医院
He's in very poor health. He was taken to the hospital.
他都不知道自己是谁 在哪里 他很糊涂
He doesn't seem to know who or where he is. He's very confused.
我跟Hernandez先生说了 Benjamin是我们的一员
I was telling Mr. Hernandez that Benjamin is one of us.
如果他需要住的地方 就住这里吧
If he needs a place to stay, it's all right, he can stay here.
Benjamin
Benjamin?
你弹得真好
You play beautifully.
他好像不喜欢被人碰
He doesn't seem to like to be touched.
他记性时好时坏 认不得人
He goes in and out of states of recognition.
医生说 他们也无能为力
The doctors say, if they didn't know any better,
他已经有痴呆初期的症状了
he has the beginnings of dementia.
你记得我吗
Do you remember me?
我是Daisy
I'm Daisy.
我是Benjamin
I'm Benjamin.
很高兴认识你 Benjamin
It's nice to meet you, Benjamin.
你介意我和你坐一起吗 我想听你弹
Would you mind if I sit with you? I would love to hear you play.
我认识你吗
Do I know you?
- 我想吃早饭  - 从此之后
- I want some breakfast. - And every day,
我每天都会去看他过得怎么样
I would stop by to make sure that he was comfortable.
- 不 我没吃  - 你刚吃完
- No, I didn't. - You just finished eating.
别以为我不知道你们在搞什么
Don't think I don't know what you're doing!
你们都他妈是骗子
You're all fucking liars!
他不相信他刚吃过早饭了
He doesn't believe he just had his breakfast.
我们来看看
Now, why don't we see
能不能找点别的事情做呢
if we can't find something else for you to do?
我总觉得 有很多事情我都记不得了
I have a feeling there's a lot of things I can't remember.
比如什么呢 宝贝
Well, like what, sugar?
比如 我好像活了很久
It's like there's this whole life I had,
但却不记得我的人生
and I can't remember what it was.
没事
It's okay.
忘记事情没什么的
It's okay to forget things.
很多时候 他不记得自己是谁 在哪
Many times, he would simply forget who or where he was.
在那儿 屋顶上
There he is, he's up there on the roof.
照顾他不容易
It wasn't easy.
- Benjamin  - 我可以看到一切
- Benjamin! - I can see everything!
- 我能看见大河  - 没错
- I can see the big river! - That's right,
你什么都能看到 宝贝
you can see everything, sweetheart.
我能看见妈妈的墓地
I can see the graveyard where Mama's buried,
- 还有很多其他的人  - 快下来
- and all those other people. - I want you to come down!
- 我要是会飞呢  - 我就认识个会飞的人
- What if I could fly? - I knew a man who could fly.
你下来 我就告诉你他的故事
You come down and I'll tell you all about him.
快上去接他
Somebody go up there.
我搬进去的时候 他5岁
He was five when I moved in.
跟我遇见他时差不多大
Nearly the same age I was when I had met him.
"这是一只老袋鼠下午5点的样子"
"This is the picture of Old Man Kangaroo 5 in the afternoon
"他有着粗壮漂亮的后腿"
"When he had got his beautiful hind legs."
时间流逝
The days passed.
我看着他 他不再会走路
And I watched as he forgot how to walk
- 也不会说话  - 我叫什么呀
- and how to talk. - What's my name?
我叫Daisy
I'm Daisy.
你会说"Daisy"吗
Can you say "Daisy"?
2002年 火车站换了新的钟表
In 2002, they put up a new clock in that train station.
2003年春天
And in the spring of 2003,
他看着我
he looked at me
我知道他认出了我
and I knew that he knew who I was.
然后 他闭上眼睛 好像睡着了
And then he closed his eyes as if to go to sleep.
- 真希望我能认识他  - 现在不就认识了
- I wish I'd known him. - Now you do.
妈 我去看看怎么回事
Mom, I think I should go see what's going on.
晚安 Benjamin
Good night, Benjamin.
河堤崩塌之后会有山洪
We're expecting flash flooding after the levee break.
已经在9区暴发
It occurred in the Ninth Ward.
有些人生来就注定可以坐在河边
Some people are born to sit by a river.
有些人生来就注定被闪电击中
Some get struck by lightning.
有些人生来就注定懂音乐
Some have an ear for music.
有些人生来就注定是艺术家
Some are artists.
有些人生来就注定是游泳健将
Some swim.
有些人生来就注定懂纽扣生意
Some know buttons.
有些人生来就注定知道莎士比亚
Some know Shakespeare.
有些人生来就注定做母亲
Some are mothers.
有些人生来就注定是舞者
And some people dance.
电波字幕组 欢迎您的加入
官方网站:www.dbfansub.com
新浪微博:@电波字幕组